<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ministers dues and peoples duty; or A bill of accounts between ministers and people: shewing vvhat people owe unto their ministers; which may also serve to mind ministers, what they are to expect from their people. By Sam. Clark M.A. sometimes fellow of Pembroke-Hall in Cambridg, and now minister of Grendon Under-wood in Buckinghamshire.</title>
            <author>Clark, Samuel, 1626-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1057_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204352</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863906</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863906</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79883)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 156:E1057[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ministers dues and peoples duty; or A bill of accounts between ministers and people: shewing vvhat people owe unto their ministers; which may also serve to mind ministers, what they are to expect from their people. By Sam. Clark M.A. sometimes fellow of Pembroke-Hall in Cambridg, and now minister of Grendon Under-wood in Buckinghamshire.</title>
                  <author>Clark, Samuel, 1626-1701.</author>
                  <author>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A.M. for William Miller at the Golden Acorn in St Pauls Church-yard, near the little north-door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Richard Baxter.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The peoples duty to their pastors.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 29 1660"; the second 1 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Salaries, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116122:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Miniſters Dues AND PEOPLES DUTY; <hi>OR</hi> A BILL of ACCOUNTS BETWEEN Miniſters and People: SHEWING VVhat <hi>People</hi> owe unto their <hi>Miniſters;</hi> which may alſo ſerve to mind <hi>Miniſters,</hi> what they are to expect from their <hi>People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Sam. Clark</hi> M. A. ſometimes Fellow of <hi>Pembroke</hi>-Hall in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg,</hi> and now Miniſter of <hi>Grendon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-wood</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. 13.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your ſouls, as they that muſt give account, that they may do it with joy, and not with grief, for that is unprofitable for you.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Curant, &amp; ſanant haec amara, quamvis ſenſum exaſperent.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Clemens Alex.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>William Miller</hi> at the Golden Acorn in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, near the little North-door, 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116122:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116122:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipfull S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>RICHARD PIGOT</hi> OF <hi>Dotherſhall</hi> Knight, His honoured Patron, Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was one of the <hi>ſtatute-Lawes</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh Theocracy,</hi> that, <hi>If a Maſter gave his ſervant a wife,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 21.4.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhe did bear him ſons or daughters, the wife and her children ſhould be her Maſters.</hi> An Eccleſiaſticall Benefice, is by ſome Authors called a <hi>wife:</hi> ſuch a <hi>wife, endowed</hi> with a competent <hi>Portion,</hi> you were pleaſed freely and undeſervedly to beſtow upon me: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us this <hi>tender Infant</hi> (this weak Tractate) is <hi>brought forth,</hi> which by the tenor and obligation of the former Law, belongs to you. Will you now be pleaſed to own it upon this conſideration, and <hi>look upon it</hi> for its <hi>relative,</hi> though not for any <hi>reall</hi> inherent worth; and to let ſome drops of that love and kindneſs, which you have done, and do continually pour upon the head of its unworthy Author, fall down upon it. Let that pity, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and hoſpitality, which all ſorts do ſo frequently
<pb facs="tcp:116122:3"/> experiment, be extended to this poor expoſed birth. Beſides, as you are <hi>Lord</hi> of the <hi>Mannour</hi> in which it was firſt conceived and born, ſo it owes <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> to you, and I am confident is ready to pay <hi>ſuit and ſervice</hi> to you, according to its utmoſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity and poſſibility. Will you be pleaſed but to make triall of its ſervice, and ſee what; it can do for you, and hearken to its voice, as <hi>Naaman</hi> to the little maides, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.2, 4, 5. And though 'tis true, you ſtand not in need of ſuch a ſervant, yet it may ſtand in need of ſuch a Maſter: and therefore it begs the favour of one of your retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which I likewiſe crave in its behalf, that it may ſerve as a publike monument of my gratitude, and teſtifie to all that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt obliged and devoted Servant, <hi>Samuel Clarke.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:116122:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Readers;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it hath long been the happineſs of this unworthy Land, to have had great ſtore of faithfull Paſtors (and long may it ſo continue) ſo is it the aggravated unhappineſs of too many, that they know not the worth and uſe of this mercy; but loſe it, and turn it to the increaſe of their ſin and miſery, by contemptuous diſeſteem, ſupine neglect, or obſtinate diſobedience. Some uſe the name and ſhaddow of the Miniſtry to quiet their conſciences, while they live a worldly fleſhly life, and are ſtrangers to the Spirit and power of the Goſpel, and perhaps abhorre, or at leaſt refuſe, to live by faith, a holy and heavenly converſation: as if the Miniſtry were appointed by certain formalities to bleſs the ungodly and the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, whom God condemneth; and to charm thoſe into Heaven, that God hath ſaid ſhall not come there. Others do honour them, while they humour <hi>them</hi> in their <hi>opinions,</hi> or croſs them not in the way of their ſenſuality, ambition, covetouſneſs, or outſide hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſelf-deceiving Religion. But if Paſtors will be
<pb facs="tcp:116122:4"/> 
               <hi>Paſtors,</hi> guiding, and not following the humours of the people; and if they will be <hi>faithfull,</hi> reſolving rather to <hi>profit,</hi> than by <hi>flattery</hi> or ſinfull <hi>ſilence</hi> and <hi>omiſſions</hi> and <hi>complyances</hi> to pleaſe, they ſhall then be the object of the anger of ſome, the cenſures of others, the ſcorns of too many, and it's well if not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge and perſecution. Were Lawyers as deſpitefully, contemptuouſly, and unworthily uſed by their clients, and Phyſicians by their Patients, and the Teachers of any Languages, Arts, or Sciences, by their Diſciples, you may eaſily conjecture how it would be born, and what would be the effects and conſequences. But it ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ms it is Heaven only, and the way and guides that lead to Heaven, that muſt be patiently ſleighted, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified and abuſed. And if our bleſſed Lord, the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of our ſalvation, in whom they profeſs to place all <hi>their</hi> hopes, muſt practically be rejected, it beſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not his ſervants to be impatient of mens ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and contempt. Readers, becauſe as it is not <hi>having food,</hi> but <hi>eating</hi> it that muſt nouriſh you, nor <hi>having cloathes,</hi> but <hi>wearing</hi> them that muſt keep you warm, nor <hi>having</hi> a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> but opening your ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to him, and taking and following his advice, that muſt cure you; ſo it is not <hi>having faithfull Paſtors,</hi> but underſtanding their office, and uſe, and applying your ſelves to them for neceſſary advice in publike and private, and ſubmitting to their holy Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that muſt make you ſavingly partakers of the bleſſing of their Office and labours. We recommend this Sermon to your peruſall, and practice, which with plainneſs and brevity acquainteth you more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with your duties, in relation to thoſe that are over
<pb facs="tcp:116122:4"/> you in the Lord, beſeeching you to believe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that if you own, defend, and maintain your Teachers, and yet do not <hi>heartily</hi> and <hi>reſolvedly</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain and obey the heavenly meſſage which they bring you, you are in the way to Hell among Sermons and holy Ordinances, as well as Heathens are, that ſin in greater darkneſs. He that hath ears to hear, let him hear. I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb. 10. 1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your faithfull Monitor. <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:116122:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is an effect which falls under the common obſervation of the narroweſt and moſt unapprehenſive capacities. <hi>That many things do move con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their proper and particular inclination for the generall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and good of the Univerſe:</hi> The <hi>cauſe</hi> where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Philoſophers aſſigne to be, <hi>ne detur vacuum.</hi> A conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>deration of ſomething parallell to this in morality, hath moved me, contrary to my generall reſolution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſuch attempts, to cloſe with thoughts of the publication of my weake endeavours upon this ſubject. For having occaſion to take notice that (as far as my little reading and intelligence would enable me to diſcerne) this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is not ſo fully and thorowly handled as might be deſired by any one of thoſe many that have written of <hi>Relative duties,</hi> and yet it being of ſo great concernment for the peace and ſettlement of the Church, eſpecially after our ſad diſtractions and diviſions, and for the reducing of things into ſome order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I thought ſuch a ſorry b ſh might ſerve to ſtop this gap, till ſome better materials were provided, and a more effectuall remedy adminiſtred, by an abler band: So that as peoples neglect of their duty firſt moved me to preach on this Subject; ſo want of ſufficient meanes thorowly to know their duty, prevailed with me to print it.<note place="margin">Oportet eum qui inſtruit rudes animos talem eſſe, qui pro in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> audito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum poſſit ſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare. <hi>Gratian.</hi>
               </note> And as you ſee it is ſet out in a plain garb, and familiar ſtyle, as being <hi>calculated</hi> for the <hi>Meridian</hi> of Country-capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which uſually for the generality are not of any great <hi>latitude;</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome of the particulars here publiſhed were omitted in the Preaching, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in all probability they would have flown over the heads of moſt, if not of all of my hearers: and I deſire to ſhoot juſt breaſt-high, and to aim eſpecially at the hearts, or however never above the heads of my Auditors. Again, other paſſages may ſeem to ſome <hi>abominable truths,</hi> which they are unwilling to hear and take notice of, and yet they cannot tell how to gainſay; but if truths, they muſt not be alwayes thrown aſide and diſregarded; they muſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be alwayes concealed by Miniſters, nor neglected by people: and what more fitting ſeaſon for the declaring of them, then ſuch an opportunity? And laſtly, ſome things may be diſputable, which all do not agree in; concerning which, if any one ſhall vouchſafe <hi>noſtras eſſe aliquid putare nugas,</hi> and ſo far inhance the price of them, as to render them conſiderable by a publick refutation, yet I do not take my ſelf bound to enter the liſts with any one in their defence, and to engage in ſuch a quarrel; for my deſign (as hath been ſaid) was only to acquaint people with their (much neglected) duty, wherein I have given them my judgement of what came in my way: if any be otherwiſe minded in any of the particulars, I ſhall not quarrel with them. There are too many differences in the Church already <hi>de larâ caprinâ,</hi> about theſe extra eſſential points, which have made it very<note n="*" place="margin">Litigandi pruritus eſt Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae ſcabies. <hi>Wotton.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſcabbed.</hi> I had rather <hi>ſtroke</hi> than <hi>ſcratch</hi> it, be a <hi>peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker</hi> than a <hi>peace marrer.</hi> My aim is to quicken thoſe that are remiſs, to practiſe, not to provoke the learned to contend. And if this Diſcourſe may be any way uſefull to thee in this way, give God the glory, and pray for a further bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon his endeavours, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, S. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116122:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Theſſal. 5.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And we beſeech you, Brethren,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſubject of theſe words, though,<note place="margin">Introduction.</note> it may be, not ſo <hi>toothſome and acceptable</hi> to ſome palates, yet, I am ſure, it is both <hi>wholſome and profitable,</hi> yea and neceſſary too; there being no way to Heaven but by <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 14.6.</note>; no way to Chriſt but by <hi>Faith</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 1.12.</note>; no way to faith but by <hi>Hearing</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ro. 10.14.</note>; no way to hear but by a <hi>Preacher</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ro. 10.14.</note>; no likelihood of profiting by what he preaches, without ſome eſteem of, and affection to, both his doctrine and perſon<note n="e" place="margin">Mar. 6.4, 5.</note>, and a competent performance of the other duties hereafter to be mentioned. And therefore conſulting rather how to <hi>profit</hi> then to <hi>pleaſe</hi> people, I have made choice of theſe words to be handled at this time: which I may call <hi>The peoples directory,</hi> how to carry themſelves toward their Miniſters. I gloſs them thus:</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116122:6"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Explication.</note>
               <hi>And]</hi> or, <hi>But.</hi> i. e. Though <hi>private charitative</hi> edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, (mentioned in the words immediately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding the Text) be to be endeavoured, yet not to the prejudice and diſadvantage of <hi>publike and authoritative.</hi> Duties muſt not ſtarv, eat up, or juſtle out one another. No; <hi>God will have mercy and ſacrifice both,</hi> in this ſenſe.</p>
            <p>—<hi>we]</hi> The Miniſters and Meſſengers of Chriſt, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by him <hi>to bind and looſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Lightf.</hi> Harm. of N.T. Sect. 52.</note> i. e. (according to the common uſe of that phraſe among <hi>Jewiſh</hi> writers) to teach you what is lawfull, what unlawfull; what you ought to do, and what to forbear: And more particularly and eſpecially, I <hi>Paul,</hi> who am guided by the unerring Spirit of God in what I now write to you, and require of you,</p>
            <p>—<hi>beſeech] Though we might be much bold in Chriſt, (i. e.</hi> in his Name, and by vertue of that authority he hath given us) <hi>to enjoyn you that which is</hi> fitting and <hi>convenient,</hi> and require your obedience thereto; <hi>yet for loves ſake,</hi> to ſhew our affection and love to you, and our gentleneſs and mildneſs towards you, <hi>we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech</hi> and entreat, as if it were ſome great courteſie and kindneſs to our ſelves, whenas it is your own greateſt concernment.</p>
            <p>—<hi>you]</hi> The private members of the Church of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> and in you, all Chriſtians of your rank and place to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>—<hi>Brethren]</hi> Though, 'tis true, you be our younger Brethren, as I may ſo ſay, (for we are Elders) and ſo ought to be guided by us, yet becauſe you are our brethren, and children of the ſame Father and Mother, therefore we deal thus gently, lovingly, and reſpectful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with you.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116122:6"/>
            <p>—<hi>to know]</hi> Which is not meant of a bare <hi>perſonall,</hi> but of a <hi>practicall</hi> knowledge, (for, <hi>verba ſenſus,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>i. e.</hi> ſo to carry your ſelves as befits the relation you ſtand in.</p>
            <p>—<hi>them that labour among you]</hi> i. e. your Miniſters; whoſe calling is a painfull, laborious imployment, how ſleight ſoever ſome make of it: for <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Much ſtudy,</hi> or, <hi>reading</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which <hi>Luther</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>predigon,</hi> preaching,) <hi>is a wearineſs to the fleſh,</hi> ay and to the <hi>ſpirits</hi> too, ſpending them more then any bodily exerciſe whatſoever; as appears by thoſe conſumptions, apoplexies, and ſuch like diſeaſes, which Miniſters are more ſubject to then others.</p>
            <p>—<hi>and are over you in the Lord]</hi> Whom God hath ſet to be your ſpirituall <hi>Parents,</hi> to beget you unto God; and <hi>Nurſes,</hi> to feed you with the <hi>ſincere milk of the word;</hi> and <hi>Guides,</hi> to direct you in your way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> to counſell you for your ſouls good. And therefore though you be never ſo high and much above them in other reſpects, yet in theſe reſpects they are above you, yea above the higheſt. For as Miniſters are no where in Scripture exempted from the ſecular power, ſo nor<note n="*" place="margin">I grant that Cleries both may and ought to diſplay their colours and enſignes of their cenſures againſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Oath, do raiſe &amp; make open warre againſt Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>King</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames's <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of right of Kings againſt Card.</hi> Petron. <hi>p.</hi> 113. <hi>Edit. in</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> Magiſtrates from the Eccleſiaſticall; but if there be an [<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 13.1.</hi> Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers.</note> 
               <hi>omnis anima</hi>] that reaches Miniſters; ſo there's a [<note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 20.23. <hi>Whoſeſoever ſins ye remit,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>cujuſcunque</hi>] that includes Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>—<hi>and admoniſh you,]</hi> or, <hi>inſtruct you.</hi> Where you are faulty, they muſt deal plainly and truly with you, and reprove you for your miſcarriages, and teach you how to behave your ſelves better, and as becomes Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p>The words thus opened and anatomized, ſhew you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116122:7"/> ſomething that concerns the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and ſomething that concerns the <hi>People</hi> or <hi>Populary;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diviſion.</note> That which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns Miniſters is, A deſcription of them, both by their <hi>dignity,</hi> that <hi>they are over their people in the Lord;</hi> and by their <hi>duty,</hi> more generally, <hi>they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour among you;</hi> and more eſpecially, <hi>they admoniſh you,</hi> or <hi>inſtruct you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which concerns the People, is their Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Miniſters, <hi>viz. to know them;</hi> and this earneſtly preſſed upon them, by a moſt friendly and patheticall ſupplication, <hi>We beſeech you, Brethren;</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting both the weightineſs and concernment of this duty; as alſo the neceſſity of performing it.</p>
            <p>Hence many Doctrines might eaſily be raiſed, but I ſhall only take up that point that lies uppermoſt next my hand, and which is the principall intendment of the words; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Obſervation.</note>
               <hi>God expects and requires of people, that they ſhould carry and behave themſelves towards their Miniſters, as is befitting ſuch a relation: that they ſhould diligently perform all thoſe duties towards their Miniſters that he hath commanded them.</hi> The 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Commandment en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns the duties of all relations; now there being a neer, and neceſſary relation between <hi>Paſtor</hi> and <hi>people,</hi> the duties of each, and therefore of people to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, as well as of Paſtors to their people, are there commanded. But you will find the full proof of the Point in thoſe ſeverall particular duties which people owe to their Miniſters, which are as follow. High Eſtimation; Singular Affection, Diligent Attendance, Ready Obedience, Patient Submiſſion, Humble Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Holy Imitation, Carefull preſervation of their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116122:7"/> Credit, Cheerfull Maintenance, Fervent Prayer, and Gratefull Memoriall. Where, by the way, pray you take notice, that I <hi>lay upon you no other,</hi> or greater <hi>burden, than theſe neceſſary things</hi> plainly held forth in Scripture.</p>
            <p>The firſt duty that people owe to their Miniſters (for I begin with thoſe which are next neighbours to the Text) is</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A high Eſteem and Account of them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">High Eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>Eſteem them very highly,</hi> ver. 13. Marke: An ordinary Eſteem will not ſerve the turn: He contents not himſelf with the bare word of <hi>[Eſteem]</hi> but adds two other words to ſet forth the <hi>wonderfull high eſteem</hi> you ſhould have of them. 'Tis not enough to eſteem them after an ordinary manner as you do other men, but you muſt eſteem them <hi>Highly,</hi> or<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>abundantly:</hi> nor is that yet enough, but you muſt do it<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>over and above abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly,</hi> or <hi>beyond meaſure,</hi> as a phraſe<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> very neer of kin to it is rendred, <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.21.</p>
            <p>The like expreſſion is not uſed concerning any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of men what ever. 'Tis but<note n="d" place="margin">1 Pet 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>Honour the King:</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 9.12.</note> 
               <hi>Honour thy Father and Mother</hi> [Honour] barely, without any more adoe; but here 'tis <hi>Eſteem them very highly.</hi> This is elſewhere called <hi>Double-Honour,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.17. A <hi>ſingle</hi> is not ſufficient. They muſt have <hi>a double portion</hi> of Honour to other men: not only a <hi>Child's portion,</hi> but a <hi>Firſt-borns portion,</hi> into whoſe place they are adopted<note n="f" place="margin">Numb. 3 12.</note>. People are commanded alſo to <hi>Hold them in reputation,</hi> Phil. 2.29. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Esteem them precious</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>So the word is rendred,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.4, 6.</note>, your Jewels and treaſures; or <hi>Honourable</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">h</hi>, accounting their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>feet</hi> (much more their other parts) <hi>beautifull,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116122:8"/> Rom.</hi> 10.15. Thus the <hi>Galatians</hi> prized and rated <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">So Luk 14.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Gal. 4 14. Acts 10.25. <hi>a more honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable man then thou.</hi>
               </note> when they counted him <hi>as an Angel of God, yea even as Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> and <hi>Cornelius, Peter,</hi> when he gave him ſuch extraordinary reverence and reſpect: and indeed a little too much; as appears by <hi>Peters</hi> words, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. And the people of <hi>Antioch, Chryſoſtom,</hi> when they cried out upon his ſilencing, <hi>ſatius eſt ut Sol non luceat, quam Chryſoſtomus non doceat:</hi> better that the Sun ſhould be eclipſed, then <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced. Yea thus did <hi>Joaſh,</hi> an Idolater, value and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> when he cried out, upon <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſha</hi>'s being ſick, <hi>O my father, my father, the charet of Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ael and the horſemen thereof.</hi> Nay the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens (who therefore will riſe up in judgment againſt many Chriſtians) ſet ſuch a high price upon their diabolicall Votaries,<note place="margin">2 King. 12.14.</note> that one of the Romane Conſuls riding in his chariot, and ſeeing a Prieſt and ſome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall Virgins going on foot, deſcended and would not go into it again, till they were firſt placed.</p>
            <p>Yet miſtake me not in this point: I would not be underſtood to ſpeak ſo much of outward reſpect; we do not ſtand ſo much upon that. I do not ſay, the Honour you owe to us, is ſuch as is due to Magiſtrates, and the great men of the world: we do not challenge to our ſelves, either that civill authority, or thoſe titles, or that outward pomp and ſtate, or that wealth and abundance that is due to them. No; our meſſage is ſpirituall, our Maſter is heavenly, and his Kingdom is not of this world, and therefore his Officers muſt not gape after worldly Honour. But, as in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants he looks principally to the heart, and will be worſhipt in ſpirit, ſo that honour that belongs to us,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116122:8"/> is chiefly inward and ſpirituall; conſiſting eſpecially in a high eſteem of the Excellency, Neceſſity, and Utility of our calling and emplyment. And yet withall, as we muſt ſerve God with our bodies, as well as our ſouls, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. and it is as impoſſible there ſhould be true inward devotion without ſome outward expreſſions ſome time or other, as for an opacous body to be in the light of the Sun without caſting a ſhadow; ſo let me tell you, that where there is an inward Honour and reſpect, it is impoſſible, but that that man that underſtands himſelf, ſhould make fome outward manifeſtation thereof in a civill way; which, particularly, in this caſe, muſt be done, partly in <hi>words,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.1. <hi>Rebuke not an Elder, but entreat him as a Father. Rebuke not,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Jerke him not, laſh him not, chaſtiſe him not with the ſcourge of the tongue; handle him not roughly; box him not about the ears with any uncivill, diſreſpectfull lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, by prating to him, as <hi>Diotrephes</hi> did, 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>Ep. Joh. v.</hi> 10. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>prating with evill words.</hi> You muſt not talke to them ſaucily, malepert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, impudently, inſolently, ſharply, roughly, ſlightingly, or any way unhandſomely: but <hi>entreat them as Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> ſpeak reverently, ſubmiſſively, humbly, reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to them, as children to their Parents. If you find any thing rebukeable in them, you muſt tell them of it in an humble manner, and <hi>entreat</hi> them to be more cautious for the time to come: and partly in <hi>gesture,</hi> by a reſpectfull carriage towards them: as <hi>Obadiah</hi> the Governour of King <hi>Ahab</hi>'s houſe, meeting with <hi>Elijah, fell on his face</hi> before him. <hi>Cultum exhibens, non ut Petro Cornelius, aut Johannes Angelo, Divinum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 18.1.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116122:9"/> 
               <hi>nec merè tamen, ut fratres Joſepho, civilem, ſed ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualem quendam, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eo nomine quod eſſet Propheta: qualis erit &amp; Angelis, ſicubi ſpectantur, tribuendus,</hi> ſaith the Author of the Anonymous Annot. printed <hi>Cantabr.</hi> 1653.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 28.14.</note> Even King <hi>Saul</hi> alſo <hi>ſtooped with his face to the ground, and bowed himſelf</hi> before him, whom he conceived to be <hi>Samuel.</hi> And <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſeph. Antiq.</hi> l. 11. c. 8.</note> when he ſaw <hi>Jaddua</hi> the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> alighted from his horſe, and humbled himſelf with much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence unto him: and, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> when he entred into the Synod of <hi>Nice,</hi> bowed himſelf very low unto the Biſhops there aſſembled, and ſate not down untill they deſired him. And well may it be thus, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould ſo highly Eſteem, Honour and Reverence their Miniſters, ſince</p>
            <p>Their Calling is the moſt honourable in the world: for,<note place="margin">Mal. 2.7. 2 Cor. 5.20.</note> they are <hi>Meſſengers</hi> (or <hi>Angels) of the Lord of Hoſts; and Embaſſadors of God.</hi> Now a ſpeciall Meſſenger is a Meſſenger ſent after an honourable manner from ſome great perſonage to repreſent his own perſon: and therefore the dignity of an Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors place is greater or leſs according to the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of his Maſter that ſends him. They then being Embaſſadors of God, who is <hi>King of Kings and Lord of Lords,</hi> ſent in his own<note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> ſtead, their Calling muſt needs be honourable in a ſpirituall way, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Hence alſo they are called, Angels, Elders, Rulers, Overſeers, Fathers, Lights, all which call for and beſpeak, eſteem, honour, and reſpect. Yea even many who ſeem in their words moſt to vilifie and undervalue the Miniſtry, yet by their actions diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a high eſteem of it; in that they invade it with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116122:9"/> ſo much eagerneſs, and earneſtneſs. For who goes a wooing to a poor forlorn maid or widdow that hath nothing of worth in her? This then being their due, as you have ſeen, <hi>Render to them their due—honour to whom honour belongs,</hi> Rom. 13.7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond due is, <hi>Singular Love and Affection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Singular Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. <hi>Magis ac ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis charos duca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> Beza. Gal. 4.15. Rom. 16.4.</note> 
               <hi>Eſteem them very highly in love.</hi> Or, <hi>Count them more than exceedingly dear.</hi> They muſt have a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialty in their peoples affection. Thus the <hi>Galatians</hi> loved <hi>Paul</hi> ſo entirely that they <hi>would have pul'd out their own eyes to have done him good.</hi> So did <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> when <hi>for his life they laid down their own necks:</hi> reſolved to ſtick cloſe to him whatever it coſt them. And good <hi>Obadiah</hi> came not behind any of them in love, when, not without adventure of his life, he hid the Lords Prophets in caves,<note place="margin">1 King. 18.4.</note> from the rage of <hi>Jezabel. Alexander</hi> the Great was wont to ſay, that he was more beholding to his Maſter <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> then to his Father <hi>Philip,</hi> for that he had his <hi>being</hi> only from the one, and his <hi>well-being</hi> from the other. And ſurely if we owe love to our <hi>naturall pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> as authors of our <hi>temporall life;</hi> how much more is due to our <hi>ſpirituall parents,</hi> who have begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten us by the <hi>immortall ſeed of the word, unto a bleſſed and eternall life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly 'tis but equall that people ſhould thus intirely love their Miniſters, becauſe their Miniſters do moſt paſſionately affect them. Witneſs that ſtrange wiſh of <hi>Paul, I could wiſh that my ſelf were accurſed</hi> (or ſeparate) <hi>from Chriſt, for my brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.3.</note> 
               <hi>my kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men according to the fleſh.</hi> Where ſome lay the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis upon the word <hi>[could,]</hi> q.d. if it were poſſible
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116122:10"/> to be done,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Balls</hi> Power of godlineſs. p. 8.</note> and lawfull to be deſired, I <hi>could</hi> find in my heart to do it. Others thus: He doth not wiſh to be made the enemy of Chriſt, but only, not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the bleſſed viſion of Chriſt: not of an elect perſon to be made a reprobate, but, remaining a choſen veſſel, to be deprived of the glory of the elect, that his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren might be ſaved; however it was a high and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtrain of heroicall love. So 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Being</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an emphaticall word, not uſed elſewhere in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying to be in a manner, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verborn with earneſt deſire.</note> 
               <hi>affectionately deſirous of you, we were willing to have imparted to you, not the Goſpell of God only, but our own ſouls alſo, becauſe ye were dear unto us.</hi> True, the <hi>Galatians</hi> would have parted with their eyes for <hi>Paul;</hi> ay, but he would part with his ſoul (<hi>i. e.</hi> his life; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by pains in preaching, or by perſecution) for the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> here. See alſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4. and 12.15. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. <hi>per totum. Phil.</hi> 1.7, 8. and 2.20. And this alſo is the temper of every faithfull Miniſter in ſome meaſure; as appears by their readineſs to ſpend and be ſpent in the ſervice of their peoples faith. Now then, if there be but the leaſt ſpark of good nature in you, this cannot but ingage you in the ſtrongeſt bonds of love to them again. <hi>Magnes amoris, amor.</hi> And therefore if you will not <hi>amorem impendere,</hi> freely vouchſafe them your love, yet are you bound, <hi>amorem rependere,</hi> to requite their love with love. But yet withall obſerve, that you muſt not love them meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor only upon this account, becauſe they love you, nor yet for the excellency of their gifts, cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, liberality, or the like; but principally, <hi>for their works fake;</hi> becauſe they teach you to know God,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ. hom. in <hi>1 Theſ. 5.12.</hi> Et paulo poſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they are the inſtruments of your converſion and regeneration; open Heaven gates unto you; make
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116122:10"/> you partakers of a Kingdom; inform you of your duty, reprove you for ſtepping aſide, and admoniſh you of your miſcarriages; for this is part of their work, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. and for <hi>this works ſake,</hi> you muſt count them dear; even for their admonition, and reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as well as for their exhortation, and conſolation. This is right love, and indeed ſuch a love, as that they which can find it in their ſouls, may take much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort therein, as being a very good ſign of ſincerity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Diligent Attendance</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diligent At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance.</note> upon them for Inſtruction, whereby firſt people muſt ſeek unto their Miniſters <hi>privately</hi> for ſatisfaction and reſolution in any thing they are ignorant of, or ſcrupulous about: So they are directed to do, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7. <hi>The Prieſts lips ſhould keep knowledg, and they</hi> (the people) <hi>ſhould ſeek the Law at his mouth:</hi> not only, out of their own brains, nor out of their books. It's no praiſe for them to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſelf-taught; as <hi>Auſtin</hi> reports of <hi>Anthony</hi> the Monk: leſt they have cauſe to complain with <hi>Jerom, Having no other guid whom I might follow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nullum praevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſequens, peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum memetip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum habeo.</note> 
               <hi>I had the worſt Maſter that could be,</hi> viz. <hi>my ſelf.</hi> But they muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, taught of God, inwardly by his Spirit, outwardly by his Miniſters. Hence <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> was appointed by the <hi>Angel</hi> to ſend for <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 10.5, 6.9.6. Hag. 2.11.</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> is ſent by Chriſt himſelf to <hi>Ananias</hi> for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and God ſends the people to the Prieſts to be reſolved in a Law-caſe. And it is obſervable, that this was the ordinary practiſe of the Diſciples, when Chriſt had taught any thing in publike which they underſtood not; to ask him privately about it. <hi>Mark</hi> 4.10. <hi>And when he was alone, they that were about him with the twelve, asked of him this Parable;</hi> i. e. the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116122:11"/> meaning of it. So again <hi>Mark</hi> 7.17. and 10.10. Yet they ſhould not enquire ſo much concerning <hi>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſputations</hi> (as the Apoſtle calls them) and <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall</hi> points (as the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> queſtioned Chriſt about the great controverſie then in faſhion,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.1.</note> between the Jews and Samaritans, concerning the place of worſhip (though there may be time and place for theſe alſo) as about <hi>practicall caſes of conſcience,</hi> that thereby they may learn rather how to <hi>do better,</hi> then to <hi>know more:</hi> which was the firſt and principall care of the Jailor, when his heart was toucht, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.30, <hi>Sirs, what muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi> So, Sir, How may I walk more holily, enjoy more communion with God, get power over ſuch a corruption? and the like? 2. They muſt watch all opportunities of <hi>publike</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; As one that attends upon another waits his leiſure, and is ready upon all occaſions; ſo people muſt be ready not only on the Lord's day, but on a week day, if opportunity be offered, to hear the word. They muſt <hi>lye daily at wiſdoms gates,</hi> Prov. 8.34. and at the pool of <hi>Betheſda.</hi> Thus the people of God are deſcribed, <hi>Calling upon,</hi> and quickning one another hereto. <hi>Eſay</hi> 2.3. <hi>Many people ſhall ſay, Come and let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of Jacob.</hi> And <hi>ſitting</hi> in his preſence. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31.—<hi>they ſit before me as my people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 122.1.</note> And <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> rejoiced in ſuch opportunities. <hi>I was glad when they ſaid unto me, Let us go into the houſe of the Lord.</hi> But eſpecially</p>
            <p n="3">3. They muſt hearken diligently, and heed, and give attention to what is delivered. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Attend to know underſtanding.</hi> Fix thy quick-ſilver mind,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116122:11"/> and <hi>ſet thy ſelf</hi> to hear, as <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> did to pray. Thus did <hi>Lydia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 16.14. Luk 19.48. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>She attended to the things that were ſpoken of</hi> Paul. And the people on Chriſt, who <hi>were very attentive to hear him;</hi> or, they <hi>hanged upon him,</hi> as Birds do on the bills of their Dams for food. They did as it were, hang their ears upon his lips. They gaped after his words.</p>
            <p>And here it may not impertinently be enquired,<note place="margin">Caſ. Conſc.</note> Whether it be lawfull for people to make a common practiſe of going from their Miniſter that God hath ſet over them, to hear another?</p>
            <p>I anſwer briefly,<note place="margin">Solut. See <hi>Hild.</hi> on <hi>Joh. 4.</hi> p. <hi>241. Baxt.</hi> Chriſtian Concord. <hi>p. 35.</hi>
               </note> It's not without good ground generally reſolved by Divines, that if the Miniſter of a place be ſuch an one as is approved by the Church of God for his ability, faithfulneſs, and diligence in his place, ſo that there is no juſt exception to be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, it is not lawfull for any of his flock to go ordinarily from him to hear another; becauſe he is in a more eſpeciall manner appointed by God to watch over them; and, it's to be ſuppoſed, that he is better acquainted with their temper and condition, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently is beter able to ſuit himſelf to their occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then another who is but a ſtranger to them, or not ſo well acquainted with them. And beſides, it would bring confuſion into places,<note place="margin">1 Cor, 14.33.</note> which God allows not of.</p>
            <p>As for that common pretence of many, that they cannot ſo well profit by their own Miniſter, as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I anſwer, If he be ſuch an one, as is before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed (for I would not be thought to be an advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate for any idle, ignorant, or inſufficient perſon, of which ſort, God knowes, too many were put into
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116122:12"/> places in theſe later times: No; let <hi>Baal</hi> plead for himſelfe, for me: but) if, I ſay, he be ſuch an one as is before mentioned, then you had need to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine your hearts, ſtrictly, whether there be no fault in your ſelves. For I muſt needs ſay, I cannot but think that <hi>generally</hi> (I will not ſay, <hi>alwayes</hi>) the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is rather in your ſelves that you do not profit, than in your Miniſter. My reaſon is plainly this. Becauſe our profiting by any mans Miniſtery depends principally,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.7.</note> nay wholly <hi>(for neither he that plants, nor he that waters, is any thing)</hi> upon the bleſſing of God, and aſſiſtance of his Spirit: and not upon any mans parts, gifts, and abilities: Inſomuch that our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, though, <hi>He ſpake as never man ſpake,</hi> Joh. 7.46. moſt graciouſly, to admiration, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.22. moſt powerfully and demonſtratively, to conviction, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.46. yet had not ſuch ſucceſs in his Miniſtry as many of his Apoſtles, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Spirit was not yet given</hi> in that plentifull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as afterwards, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.39. Now the bleſſing of God being<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 28.20.</note> promiſt, and ſo belonging as well to one true Miniſter of Chriſt as another, certainly, if there be any defect, and want of profiting, 'tis not on Gods part, but on ours. 'Tis true, God being wont to concur with meanes according to their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall capacity and efficacy, where he hath beſtowed greater gifts, it may reaſonably be ſuppoſed, that, <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> he doth concur with a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er degree of efficacy and aſſiſtance; whence wee finde the gaine anſwerable to the talents, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.15, 17. and therefore people under ſuch an eminent Miniſtery, may be more edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116122:12"/> yet it warrants not others to forſake their own Miniſter upon this account, for the Reaſons fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned.</p>
            <p>But yet to grant with the moſt; Suppoſe that any ſhould not yet be ſatisfied, but, after much experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; dealing impartially with themſelvs, they do find that they can profit far more by another than by their own Miniſter, yet they muſt not go to another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, or ordinarily without the conſent and leave of their own Miniſter. Becauſe by Gods Ordinance they owe duty to him as their Superior in all things that concern their ſouls (as ſhall be ſhewed preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) And likewiſe, they are bound to ſeek his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and give him all good encouragement, that he may do the work of his Miniſtery with <hi>joy</hi> and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.<note place="margin">Heb. 13.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Ready and chearfull obedience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ready Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note> Enjoyned plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies ſuch a ſubjection as an inferior, who counts himſelf under another, yields to him, who is over him. <hi>Gouge</hi> in loc.</note> 
               <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you;</hi> even your ordinary Paſtors. Mentioned alſo in ſeverall other places, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10. <hi>Who is there among you, that feareth the Lord, that obeys the voice of his Servant?</hi> i. e. Prieſt, or Prophet. (Where, by the way, Obſerve, That 'tis the property of one that truly fears God to obey his Miniſter,) 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. <hi>For this end did I write, that I might know the proof of you, whether ye would be obedient in all things,</hi> a large word. And 7.15. <hi>His inward affection is more abundant towards you, while he remembreth the obedience of you all, how with fear and trembling you received him.</hi> Here's a univerſality of perſons, as in the former place, of things. All perſons muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient in all things. And this was myſtically repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116122:13"/> in <hi>Ezechiels</hi> Viſion, where the wheels were guided by the four living creatures,<note n="c" place="margin">See <hi>Lightf. Deſcript. of Temple.</hi> c. 38. p. 255.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">b</hi> people, by their Paſtors and Miniſters. Thus much, I ſuppoſe will be readily and generally granted, being ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and poſitively enjoyned: all the difficulty is,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dub.</note>Concerning the extent of this Obedience: How far forth, and wherein people are bound to obey their Paſtors. This therefore we ſhall a little enquire into; and the rather becauſe ſome who yet pretend great reſpect and friendſhip to the Miniſtery, do ſo clip and reſtrain it, that they make it little more then a meer cipher, and leave ſcarce any thing, but the name thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Solut.</note>In Generall, It muſt be <hi>In all things,</hi> 2 Cor. 2.9. whereby 'tis parallel'd with, and made as large, as the obedience of children to parents, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.20. Servants to Maſters, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. and wives to their husbands, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.24. And this I ſhall branch out into three particulars. <hi>In neceſſary Duties; undetermined Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; and doubtfull points or Caſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. People muſt obey their Miniſters, <hi>In thoſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary duties plainly laid down in the Word, which they declare unto them, and in Gods name require their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to;</hi> as Sanctification of the Sabbath; perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of Family duties; diligence in frequenting the publick Aſſemblies: avoiding drunkenneſs, ſwearing, lying, <hi>&amp;c. Matth.</hi> 23.3. <hi>All therefore whatſoever they bid you obſerve</hi> (viz. not of their own heads, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Traditions of the Elders; but, which is enjoyned in the Law of God) <hi>that obſerve and do.</hi> People muſt conform to their advertiſements; both in obedience to God and them: and the neglect here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116122:13"/> is a contempt, and diſobedience againſt them, as well as againſt God; and rendred cenſurable by Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. <hi>If he neglect to hear the Church,</hi> (ſc. urging the reformation of ſcandalous miſcarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) <hi>let him be,</hi> &amp;c. And is alſo a great aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſin, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.12. <hi>He</hi> (Zedekiah) <hi>did that which was evil in the ſight of the Lord, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled not himſelf before</hi> Jeremiah <hi>the Prophet, ſpeaking to him in the name of the Lord.</hi> Therefore alſo the Lord ſaith, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.33. that <hi>when that ſhould come to paſs,</hi> (viz. which he hath threatned, <hi>verſ.</hi> 27, 29.) <hi>that they ſhould then know, that a Prophet had been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them,</hi> i. e. their own conſciences ſhould, in their afflictions, aggravate their ſin, by this circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; that the Lord had ſent his Prophets to them, and they had not regarded, or obeyed them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In thoſe circumſtances of publick worſhip, which are neceſſary in the generall, but not particularly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by God.</hi> Such are, <hi>Time;</hi> as, What hour on the Lords day to begin; how long to continue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; what dayes the Lords Supper ſhall be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and how oft; when any ſhall be baptized; what day of the Week to keep a Lecture. <hi>Place;</hi> as, Where the Aſſembly ſhall meet; where the Miniſter ſhall ſtand to read, preach, adminiſter the Sacraments; and where the people ſhall ſit to hear, receive, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whether the Corpſe ſhall be brought into the Church, or ſtand by the grave, or put into it, while the ſolemnity is performing. <hi>Geſture;</hi> as, To hear, ſitting or ſtanding; with the Hat off, or on; and ſo for the Miniſter to preach; to receive the Lords Supper ſitting, or ſtanding, or kneeling. <hi>Habit;</hi> as,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116122:14"/> Whether the Miniſter ſhall preach in a Cloak, or Gown, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of what colour or materialls his cloathes ſhall be.<note n="*" place="margin">See a full e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeration of them in <hi>Baxt.</hi> of Epiſc. <hi>p.</hi> 400.</note> Many other ſuch circumſtances there are, which being neceſſary in generall, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch, as no action can be performed without, and yet not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly determined by God now under the Goſpel, and ſo being left to the prudence of Church-guides to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine of, according to the generall Rules, of Order, Decency, Edification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> people ought to yield conformity to ſuch determinations; for if a difference ſhould ariſe concerning any of theſe circumſtances, between Paſtor and people, whether think you fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſhould ſubmit, Paſtor to flock; Ruler to ruled; or on the contrary?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Baxt.</hi> of Epiſc. <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 10.</note>3. <hi>In doubtfull points and difficult caſes,</hi> which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are ignorant in, or cannot be ſatisfied about; till they receive ſatisfaction, or underſtand them themſelves, and are able to judge of them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Whoſe faith follow.</hi> For where common people have not time, or leaſure, or ability to ſtudy all points of Divinity themſelves, whom is it more fit they ſhould hearken to, and be ruled by, then their own Paſtors and Teachers: as a wife ſhould by her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and children by their Parents? It being to be ſuppoſed ordinarily (for I ſpeak not of extraordinary caſes, which may ſometimes happen in ſome places, as in the Univerſities, or Innes of Court) that they underſtand themſelves better in theſe things then their people, becauſe it's their buſineſs and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſtudy them: And therefore as we ſee in all other caſes, men will uſually take the judgements of Artificers in matters that concern their own trade. If
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116122:14"/> you have a matter of Law, you go to Lawyers; of health, to Phyſicians; of building to Carpenters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if I were to be reſolved in a point of Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, which I underſtand not my ſelf, I would come to ſome of you that have been verſed, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced in it all your time, and take your judgement rather then mine own, becauſe it's your calling and not mine; ſo ought you in thoſe points you underſtand not, eſpecially controverſall points, to ſubmit your judgement to ours, and to conform your practice to our directions: for it being our office to teach you, it's your duty to believe us with a humane faith,<note place="margin">Oportet diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem credere.</note> in caſes where you have no evidence to the contrary. So that in caſe a Miniſter require his people to believe ſuch a point, which they know not whether it be a truth or no; or conform to ſuch a practice, which they know not whether it be lawfull or no, then the command of obeying them takes place: for the duty of obeying them being certain, and the error of the point held forth, or unlawfulneſs of the practice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, being uncertain, and unknown, and only ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, they muſt go on the ſurer ſide. But yet withall let me adde, That you are not ſo wholly to rely upon the ſuſpected judgement of a ſingle Paſtor, but that you muſt ſearch diligently after the truth, and labour to find out whether thoſe things he teaches be ſo or no, as <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. And alſo in weighty caſes apply your ſelves to the unanimous Paſtors of other Churches, for their judgement.</p>
            <p>But becauſe all obedience is founded upon autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and where there is no power to command, there is no obedience owing: therefore I ſhall briefly aſſert
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116122:15"/> the authority of Miniſters over their people: And that both</p>
            <p>Generally, from thoſe names and titles given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, which clearly hold forth as much. They are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as in the Tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and rendred, <hi>are over you,</hi> and if God hath ſet them over you, then he hath put you under them. Rendred alſo, <hi>ſuch as rule,</hi> or, <hi>Rulers,</hi> Rom. 12.8. 1 Tim. 5.17. And that as a Governour rules his family, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. and a Parent his children, <hi>ver.</hi> 12<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. and have not they power to command? Called alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7, 13, 24. Shepheards, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.36. that lead, guide, and govern their flocks. Stewards, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. Fathers, <hi>Philemon</hi> 10. All which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſuperiority, rule, and authority: and hence, they have ſometimes not only deſired, requeſted, entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and beſeeched their people (as in the Text) but peremptorily commanded them, as you may ſee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall times in one Chapter, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.4, 6, 10, 12. And alſo</p>
            <p>Particularly, in the ſeverall caſes aforementioned. As</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Baxter</hi> of Epiſc. <hi>p.</hi> 8.</note>1. That they have Authority to teach their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and declare their duty unto them, none will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. You may ſee their Commiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. Some indeed allow thus much to others, but I think none take it from them. And 'tis true, private Chriſtians may exhort, admoniſh, edifie one another; but there is as much difference between theſe and a Miniſters preaching, as between a neighbours advice, and a Juſtice of Peace his Warrant: or between a Canon charged with a Bullet, and one only with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116122:15"/> Powder, which may make as great a noiſe, but doth no execution.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning the Circumſtantialls of publike worſhip not determined in Scripture, that place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. empowers them to judge and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order</hi> All things, <hi>i. e.</hi> that he had been ſpeaking of before. <hi>viz.</hi> what language they ſhould uſe; and in what manner to exerciſe the gift of tongues and propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and others of like nature, being only neceſſary Circumſtances not determined by God (not myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Ceremonies) muſt be ordered by them, in a grave, ſober, and comely manner.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For controverſall points of faith, or practiſe; (which we call Caſes of Conſcience) which people underſtand not ſo well themſelves, their Miniſters have likewiſe power to determine; as appears by the practiſe of the Councell at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who made bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing determinations for the Church. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28. <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt, and to us, to lay upon you no greater burden, then thoſe neceſſary things.</hi> Not neceſſary in their own nature, but in that preſent jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of time, for the avoiding of offence. Even as the Prieſts under the Law had power to determine controverſies. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8, 12. and as among us Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace have at the Seſſions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Patient ſubmiſsion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Patient Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</note> in caſe of <hi>Cenſure,</hi> by Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, Suſpenſion, or Excommunication; <hi>ſubmit your ſelves,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly refers to ſome puniſhment. Not on the one hand fretting, raging, railing, and crying out, that they take too much upon them, and meddle with that that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116122:16"/> belongs not to them. What! cannot a man be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken a little, but he muſt preſently be told of it, and cenſur'd for it? Nor, on the other hand, ſlighting, and making nothing of it, and ſaying, Well! If I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament here, I can go elſewhere, where I can. If he will not give it me, yet I hope God will ſave me without him: this is far from ſubmiſſion; but to be ſenſible of your demerit, to acknowledg the juſtice of the ſentence, and to endeavour by a ſpeedy repentance and reformation to get it revok't, and your ſelves reſtored to communion with the Church again; as the inceſtuous perſon did, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. And this ſubmiſſion is due to them, upon the account of that power they have received from Chriſt, to call their people to account for their miſcarriages, and to take cognizance of ſcandalous ſins and tranſgreſſions of Gods Law, by hearing complaints and teſtimony of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.16, 17. by cenſuring, judging, or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſentence upon offenders. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Do not ye judg them that are within?</hi> and that finally and deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, ſo as that there lies no appeal from that cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. <hi>If he neglect to hear the Church,</hi> (there's no further proceſs; no appeal to the Civil Magiſtrate:<note place="margin">Levit. 13.</note> Here's the <hi>non plus ultra</hi> of theſe caſes, <hi>let him be to you,</hi> &amp;c. Even as under the Law, the Prieſts were judicially, deciſively, to determine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Lepers, and to pronounce them either clean, or unclean, and according to the Prieſts ſentence, was the perſon to be accounted to all intents and purpoſes, ſo as to be admitted, or excluded the Congregation; ſo it is here. And then in caſe of Repentance, they have power to abſolve, acquit, pronounce clean, as I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116122:16"/> may ſo ſay, and to admit to communion with the Church again; called by Chriſt <hi>looſing,</hi> or <hi>unbinding. Mat.</hi> 18.18. a metaphor ſhewing the efficacy and ſtrength of Church-cenſures: and <hi>forgiving their ſins. Joh.</hi> 20.23. And therefore I would not have people to think, they may do what they will, and have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſaid to them: profane the Sabbath and be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs: be drunkards, ſwearers, negligent in coming to Church, and yet ſcape ſcot-free. No, the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall, as well as the Civill Magiſtrate, I mean, their Paſtors, may and muſt puniſh them for ſuch miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages. And as it's a neglect of their duty, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the truſt in Juſtices of Peace, or Conſtables, to ſee the Laws of the Land broken, and take no courſe with tranſgreſſors; ſo that Miniſter neglects his duty, that ſuffers his people to live in ſuch ſins, and doth not only not reprove and admoniſh, but alſo not call them to account, and more deeply cenſure them for the ſame. And if this be not a compulſive power, and that as great, nay more, (as we ſhall ſee anon) then any Civill Magiſtrate on earth hath, then I know not what a compulſive power is. For how do Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates uſe to compell their ſubjects? Why, only in a morall, not phyſicall, or naturall way, <hi>i. e.</hi> when they forbid ſuch a practiſe, ſuppoſe murder, they do not tye the hands of all their ſubjects, but only annex a penalty to the Law, that if any tranſgreſs, they ſhall be puniſhed in ſuch a manner. So for things enjoyn'd; the penalty is the compulſion. Now this power have Miniſters; power to puniſh and <hi>revenge all diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bience,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.6. and that in a higher way, and with greater puniſhment, then any Magiſtrate on earth can
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116122:17"/> inflict. For all puniſhment inflicted by the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, is but outward, either upon the perſons body, or eſtate,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.20.</note> or both: but the puniſhment infligible by the Miniſter, or Eccleſiaſticall Magiſtrate, is ſpirituall, and reaches to the ſoul; ſo that by how much the ſoul is more valuable then the body, or eſtate, by ſo much is the puniſhment infligible by the Miniſter, more terrible and dreadfull, then any can be inflicted by the Civil Magiſtrate. Although 'tis true, becauſe men do ſo much <hi>obbruteſcere,</hi> and become <hi>like the beaſts that periſh,</hi> and are led ſo much by ſenſe, thence it comes to paſs, that they are more affected with corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, then ſpirituall puniſhments, and more fear the death of the body, then the damnation of the ſoul, and conſequently ſtand more in awe of the Laws of the Land, then of the Laws of God. Yet in it ſelf the ſpirituall puniſhment is incomparably the greater, and conſequently, there is incomparably a<note n="a" place="margin">Quod ſi homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes reputarent, metuerent ſibi plus ab Eccleſiae cenſuris, quàm à gladio &amp; virgis Reipubl. cùm Miniſtri habent poteſtatem vitae &amp; necis aeternae; ut de omnibus vel ad vitam, vel ad mortem ſententiam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. — Si è terrâ exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere &amp; extur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare ſit mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, quanto magis expellere è caelo? ſi è col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio veſtro ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem movere, quanto magis è coetu &amp; collegio Sanctorum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem excludere poſſe? <hi>Cartwr. Harm.</hi> p. <hi>560.</hi>
               </note> ſtronger obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation lies upon perſons, to obey the commands of God and his Officers, <hi>i. e.</hi> Miniſters, than the Laws of the Land and the Civil Magiſtrate: becauſe, I ſay, the ſoul is concerned in the puniſhment inflicted by the Miniſter. Now it reaches to the ſoul, inaſmuch as while perſons lye under Eccleſiaſticall Cenſures du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inflicted, they are in a ſtate of damnation (as far as man can judg of them,) becauſe their ſins are unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd. <hi>(Joh.</hi> 28.23. <hi>whoſe ſoever ſins ye retain, they are retained:)</hi> and without pardon no bleſſedneſs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1. The Kingdom of Heaven is ſhut againſt them<note n="b" place="margin">—portam coe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li ei occluſam iri, cui Eccleſiae oſtium &amp; val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas obturaverit; rem Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti illis ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam iri, cui Eccleſia Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaverit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> id. p. <hi>604.</hi> b.</note>; for God ratifies and confirms the cenſure. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19.—<hi>whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on earth ſhall be bound in Heaven:</hi> He adds his <hi>Dicu le veult,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116122:17"/> it becomes not only an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of the Church, but a <hi>Statute-Law</hi> of Heaven too: ſo that if a juſtified perſon ſhould fall under this <hi>cenſure,</hi> 'tis as impoſſible for him to die in that condition, as for <hi>David</hi> to die in the act of adultery, before repentance; ſo that in it ſelf, 'tis incomparably greater. Only here's that, that ſomething qualifies the matter, That puniſhments in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by the Civil Magiſtrate, are ſometimes purely (at leaſt perfectly) vindictive; as when they touch the life of the offender; for in that caſe there's no place left for Repentance and amendment: but now the puniſhment inflicted by the Church, is purely and perfectly (in its own nature) medicinall, aiming at the reformation and amendment of the party puniſhed: that his <hi>ſoul may be ſaved in the day of the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.5. <hi>for his edification, not deſtruction,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.8. that <hi>he may learn not to blaſpheme,</hi>) or tranſgreſs in any other particular.) 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20.</p>
            <p>So then, Lay all theſe things together, and then tell me whether Miniſters have not a compulſive, as well as a directive power. For can you imagin that a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter hath no more power over his people, than a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician over his patient? who cannot inflict the leaſt ſhadow of puniſhment upon them, for the greateſt non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obſervation of, or contrary practiſe to his directions? or that, people are no more bound to obey their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, than a patient, his Phyſician, who yet (I doubt not, but) is bound in conſcience to follow his preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions? No; 'tis certainly in it ſelf the higheſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſory power imaginable; and I ſee no reaſon, why it may not properly be called <hi>Juriſdiction;</hi> which is nothing elſe, but ſuch a commanding, as carries in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116122:18"/> a revenge againſt the diſobeyer (as the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Scholer of his time defines it;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>F. Paul.</hi> Hiſt. of Inquiſ. <hi>p.</hi> 85. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Edit. in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note>) which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> almoſt <hi>totidem verbis</hi> attributes to Miniſters in the place aforementioned. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6. <hi>Having in readineſs to revenge all diſobedience.</hi> As alſo, Why it may not be ſaid, That people ſhould obey their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, not only for conſcience ſake, but for wrath (which yet is commonly denied:) as ſubjects muſt their Magiſtrates, <hi>not only for wrath, but, for conſcience ſake,</hi> Rom. 13.5. only the obligation lies ſtronger to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Miniſters than Magiſtrates, becauſe they are more immediate deputies of Chriſt, and deal more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately for him than Magiſtrates do.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> If it be objected (as 'tis by ſome, to elevate, and extenuate their power) That all this power of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters is but<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Morrice</hi> of the Sacrament, <hi>Sect.</hi> 32. <hi>p.</hi> 300.</note> derivative, delegated, executive, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I grant it: and yet 1. However they have, at leaſt, as much power in their ſphears, as any ſubordinate Magiſtrate whatſoever (Judg, or Juſtice of Peace) in theirs; who act all in the Name of another, <hi>viz.</hi> the Supream Magiſtrate, and nothing in their own. 2. 'Tis ſo in relation to God only, and not to man: They derive not their power from man, nor are his ſervants therein. And thus, the higheſt Civil power on earth is derivative, <hi>viz.</hi> from God. True, we are our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſervants, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5.) to do them all the good we can; but yet they are not our maſters, to rule and command us.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Another duty people owe unto their Miniſters is, <hi>Humble meekneſs</hi>
               <note place="margin">Humble Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> 
               <hi>under reproof,</hi> (which though it belong properly to the former head, as a branch
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116122:18"/> thereof, yet in regard of the length of that, I ſhall handle it diſtinctly by it ſelf.) I ſay, Quiet, and meek enduring of reproof. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.22. <hi>I beſeech you, Brethren, ſuffer the word of Exhortation:</hi> which phraſe <hi>[the word of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation,]</hi> though it may be taken generally for all manner of inſtruction, whether Information, Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Admonition, or the like, yet the word <hi>[ſuffer]</hi> ſeems to aim at ſomething which was grievous and diſtaſtfull to them, and which they did not care to hear; and therefore I take it here more ſtrictly, for <hi>matter of reproof;</hi> that people ſhould willingly and patiently hearken to the reproofs of their Miniſters; take Potions as well as Cordials; ſuffer them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply corraſives, when there is occaſion, as well as leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives at other times: thus did <hi>David. Nathan</hi> doth not ſprinkle him with Court holy-water, but tells him plainly of his ſinne; <hi>Thou art the man,</hi> 2 Sam. 12.7. and threatens him grievouſly for it, <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 12. Now <hi>David</hi> doth not fret and fume at him for it, but takes it very patiently, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>And David ſaid unto Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, I have ſinned againſt the Lord.</hi> A meek and humble ſpeech! the contrary whereto, <hi>viz.</hi> fretting at, and impatience of reproof, is a moſt ſenſleſs and bruitiſh practiſe, not to be parallel'd in any caſe in the world again. For, who is angry with his Lawyer for acquainting him with the badneſs of his cauſe; or with his Phyſician for diſcovering to him the danger of his diſeaſe? or with a watchman for giving notice that his houſe is beſet, or on fire, though he be diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and affrighted thereby? Who takes it ill of a friend, that ſeeing a poiſon'd arrow or Cannon-bullet coming directly towards him, pulls him away with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116122:19"/> ſuch violence, as perhaps to pull his arm out of joint? Why then ſhould people be angry with their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for dealing plainly and impartially with them, and laying open the true ſtate of their ſouls to them, and warning them to <hi>fly from the wrath to come?</hi> And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let me tell you, that if at any time you be galled by the Miniſtry of the word, 'tis not ſo much your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, as your own <hi>conſciences that reproach you.</hi> For did you ever know a ſober man angry with a Miniſter for preaching againſt drunkenneſs; a chaſt man finde fault with a Sermon againſt uncleanneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that if you find your ſelves at any time aggrieved at a reproof, you muſt thank your ſelves, and not blame them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>An holy Imitation</hi>
               <note place="margin">Holy Imitation.</note> 
               <hi>of their Example.</hi> Phil. 3.17. <hi>Brethren, be followers together of me, and mark them which walk ſo as ye have us for an example.</hi> And that becauſe they are their ſpirituall parents. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15, 16. <hi>For though you have ten thouſand inſtructers in Chriſt, yet have ye not many Fathers: for in Jeſus Chriſt have I begotten you through the Goſpell: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you be ye followers of me.</hi> Hence Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>types</hi> or <hi>ſamplers to their flocks,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.3. People muſt learn of their Miniſters by the <hi>eye,</hi> as well as by the <hi>ear;</hi> be taught by their <hi>works,</hi> as well as their <hi>words;</hi> take recommendation and encouragement to duty, by their <hi>practiſe,</hi> as well as their <hi>preaching.</hi> If you ſee your Miniſter ſtrict in the obſervation and ſanctification of the Sabbath, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall in works of mercy and charity, peaceable, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, or exemplary in any other duty, then you muſt be carefull to dreſs your ſelves by this glaſs, to write
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116122:19"/> after this copy; otherwiſe his <hi>example</hi> will riſe up in judgment againſt you, as well as his <hi>Doctrine.</hi> Only remember, it muſt be only in matters of duty, as I ſaid, in the <hi>practiſe of piety:</hi> to follow them only ſo far forth <hi>as they follow Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.1. You muſt ſet your clock by theirs, ſo far as theirs agrees with the Sun: for if either they give a bad example, or ſay and do not, then you muſt <hi>do as they ſay, and not as they do,</hi> Mat. 23.3.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Carefull preſervation of their good name.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Carefull preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their Credit.</note> People muſt charily maintain their Miniſters credit, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be <hi>tale-bearers,</hi> and <hi>carriers</hi> about, or <hi>ſenders</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout of diſgracefull reports of them. <hi>Acts</hi> 23.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evill of the Ruler of thy people.</hi> Which doubtleſs will hold good as well concerning <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall,</hi> as <hi>Civil Magiſtrates,</hi> being here immediately applied to the High-Prieſt: as you muſt not ſpeak unhandſomely <hi>to them,</hi> (as was ſhewed afore) ſo here you are caution'd, not to ſpeak unhandſomely <hi>of them:</hi> nor be <hi>tale-bearers,</hi> or <hi>receivers</hi> and credulous in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving diſgracefull reports concerning them. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Againſt an Elder receive not an accuſation, but under two or three witneſſes.</hi> God here hath made an expreſs proviſion for the ſafety of their reputation, and ſet a ſpeciall fence and mound about their good names; ſo that they are priviledged perſons, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly exempted above others; and therefore their people ſhould be exceeding tender of their credit. Thus we read in Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory, that,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod. Hiſt.</hi> l. 1. c. 11. <hi>Socr.</hi> l. 1. c. 8.</note> when the Synod of <hi>Nice</hi> was aſſembled, by <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and ſome accuſations were preſented to the Emperour againſt ſome Biſhops and Miniſters, he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116122:20"/> lookt not on the particulars, but ſealed them up with his own Signet, and having firſt reconciled the parties, commanded the Libells to be burnt; adding withall, <q>That if he ſhould ſee a Biſhop in adultery, he would cover his nakedneſs with his own Royall Robe; for, ſaith he, the ſins of ſuch men ought not to be divulg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, leaſt their examples do as much hurt to the ſouls of others, as their fact to their own;</q> their good name being as neceſſary for others, as a good life for themſelves. And therefore you muſt be very cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious both of your <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>ears,</hi> both in telling and hearkening to any ill report of them. And truly there's great reaſon for it. Partly becauſe men are apt to <hi>hate him that reproves in the gate,</hi> Amos 5.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.16. and we know, <hi>Ill-will never ſpeaks well.</hi> Partly, becauſe men in office are moſt watcht and obſerv'd. <hi>Jeremy</hi> complains, that <hi>all his familiars watcht for his halting,</hi> Jer. 20.10. and God diſcovers thus much to <hi>Ezekiel</hi> concerning himſelf, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.30.—<hi>the children of thy people are always talking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee by the walls, and in the doors of the houſes.</hi> Yea thus was <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf ſerved and dealt withall by the Chief Prieſts and Scribes, (<hi>Luk.</hi> 20.20.) who <hi>watched him, and ſent forth ſpies, which ſhould feigne themſelves just men, that they might take hold of his words.</hi> And he warnes his Diſciples to expect the like. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.20.—<hi>if they have</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, inſidiosè obſervarunt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem meum. Sic <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittur? <hi>Mat. 27.36, 24.</hi> Gatak.</note> 
               <hi>obſerved, (or watcht,</hi> for ſo it ſhould be tranſlated) <hi>my ſayings, they will watch yours alſo.</hi> And partly, becauſe their Credit is of moſt concernment for the honour of the Goſpell. For as one would be loath to eat meat (otherwiſe whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and good) if ſerv'd up in a foul diſh; ſo even
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116122:20"/> wholſome truths will be but ſleighted, if brought by one whoſe good name is beſpattered, and beſmear'd with reproaches, whereby prejudices are entertain'd againſt him. In all which reſpects, people muſt be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefull how they give ear or credit to diſgracefull reports concerning their Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="9">9. People owe unto their Miniſters <hi>chearfull and liberall Maintenance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chearfull Maintenance.</note> Though it belongs to Miniſters only to preach the word, typified by <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſons ordering the Lamps, <hi>Exod.</hi> 27.21. yet the people muſt ſee that the Lamps be kept burning, by provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding oyl for continuall their ſupply, <hi>ver.</hi> 20.<note place="margin">Vines.</note> 
               <q>The bird that is to keep the neſt and ſit upon the eggs, muſt have her meat brought in to her, and not fly abroad to purvey for her ſelf.</q> Whatever cavils conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious perſons may make, nothing is more clear in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture than this duty, and that in the New Teſtament as well as the Old; it being an Ordinance for Goſpel-Miniſters, as well as Legall. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14.—<hi>even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpell, ſhould live of the Goſpell.</hi> q. d. As God took care of the Prieſts under the Law, to make proviſion for them, by ſeverall Laws and ordinances concerning their maintenance; ſo hath the Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> likewiſe, for Miniſters of the Goſpell: <hi>viz.</hi> Luk. 10.7, 8. <hi>In the ſame houſe remain, eating and drinking ſuch things as they give: for the labourer is worthy of his hire,</hi> i. e. deſerves to be maintained for his labour: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>meat and drink</hi> include all things requiſite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Nor makes this any thing againſt that freeneſs of preaching the Goſpell, which ſome in ſimplicity or worſe, do urge as inconſiſtent with liberall main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116122:21"/> for even the Volunteer follows not the warre at his own charges. Concerning which main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, obſerve with me theſe following particulars worthy conſideration:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it muſt not be pinching and ſcanty, but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall and plentifull. Thus it was under the Law: for though the Prieſts were not above a fourth part of the people (as<note n="a" place="margin">See D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Reyn.</hi> on Pſal. 110. <hi>p.</hi> 478.</note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Reynolds</hi> computes it) or not above a fifth or ſixth part, (according to the Learned <hi>Selden,</hi>) yet their revenues in firſt-fruits and prediall tenths, amounted to neer a fifth part of the profits of the Land (as<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Seld. <hi>Review.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> prope finem.</note> 
               <hi>Selden</hi> reckons it,) beſides their lands and many other advantages: ſo that they had above ten times as much as the ſame number of perſons of other Tribes. Now Miniſters of the Goſpell having a more excellent Miniſtry (as the Apoſtle ſhews, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.) their maintenance alſo ſhould be proportionably libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: for 'tis prophecied, that in Goſpell-times it ſhould be ſo, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 23.18. where the Prophet ſpeaking of the converſion of <hi>Tyre,</hi> and how ſhe ſhould employ her riches, when ſhe was converted, ſaith, <hi>It ſhall not be treaſured nor laid up;</hi> (viz. for any civill, common uſe, either publike or private:) <hi>for her merchandize ſhall be for them that dwell before the Lord, to eat ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, and for durable cloathing,</hi> i. e. from the Tyrian trade, (they being converted to God) means and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſhould be freely and largely afforded to God's Miniſters, for all neceſſaries and accommodations; ſo the <hi>Engliſh Annot.</hi> but more clearly, the Apoſtle gives an expreſs command, that <hi>he that is taught, ſhould communicate to his Teacher,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in all his goods,</hi> Gal. 6.6. and that Miniſters <hi>ſhould have double
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116122:21"/> honour,</hi> i. e. maintenance, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. ſo as to be able to keep hoſpitality, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This maintenance muſt be proportion'd out of the leaſt ariſing profits, as well as the greateſt: Mint, anniſe, and cummin, and all manner of hearbs ought to be tithed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.42. The Jewiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors deliver by tradition, with <hi>Selden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seld.</hi> of tithes. p. 20.</note> that all things growing out of the earth, and fit for man's meat, is titheable.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not a matter of alms, or in the nature of a free gift, but that which Miniſters have power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the people, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.4, 6, 12. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.9. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing due both by God's Ordinance, as was ſhewed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and alſo by a Law of Juſtice; they performing ſervice for it. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7, 10. <hi>Who goes a warfare any time at his own charges,</hi> &amp;c? q.d. Ask the ſouldier, husbandman, ſhepheard, whether they will ſerve you for nought; and whether they do not juſtly require recompence for their labour? And if it be but juſt to pay them, then, 'tis but juſt to recompence theſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That maintenance Miniſters receive from their people, they receive it in Gods name and ſtead; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs primarily to him, and they are but his Officers in receiving, as well as diſpenſing; and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauding of them, is robbing of God. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Will a man rob God? yet ye have robbed me: but ye ſay, wherein have we robbed him? in tithes and offerings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Whatſoever maintenance Miniſters receive from their people, yet their people can never make them amends; becauſe there is no proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween what people <hi>give to them,</hi> and what they <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116122:22"/> from their Miniſters.</hi> 1 Cor. 9.11. <hi>If we have ſown unto you ſpirituall things, is it a great thing if we reap your carnall things?</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rey.</note> q.d. If you rightly judg of thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly treaſures which we bring in abundance to you, it's impoſſible you ſhould judg our pains and ſervice towards your immortall and precious ſouls, ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rewarded with any of theſe earthly periſhable things we receive from you. And therefore <hi>Paul</hi> tells <hi>Philemon,</hi> that <hi>he owed him even his very ſelfe. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Miniſters may juſtly require maintenance of their people, though they have eſtates of their own: for thus God had expreſſely provided under the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.8. <hi>They ſhall have like portions to eat, beſide that which cometh of the ſale of his patrimony.</hi> The Prieſt muſt live of his ſervice notwithſtanding his private eſtate; the equity of which Law, belongs to the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Jus Divi. Mini. Evang. p. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note>7. Though, 'tis true, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> for ſome ſpeciall reaſons received nothing from ſome Churches, but did work with their own hands to ſupply their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, yet 1. They put it into the Catalogue of their ſorrowes and ſufferings, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 12. <hi>We labour work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with our own hands.</hi> 2. They ſtill thought that it was a Goſpell-ordinance, and aſſert their power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.4—15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17, 18. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.9. 3. They received much from others. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8. <hi>That which was lacking to me, the Brethren that came from Macedonia ſupplied,</hi> Phil. 4.16. <hi>Even in Theſſalonica ye ſent once and again to my neceſsity.</hi> And 4. He high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commends the <hi>Philippians</hi> for this their liberality towards him. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Ye did well, that ye did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116122:22"/> with my affliction.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 18.—<hi>having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of Epaphroditus the things that were ſent from you, an odor of a ſweet ſmell, a ſacrifice acceptable, well-pleaſing to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the particular proportion of Miniſters maintenance, I ſhall not meddle with the Divine right of tithes, only ſay, that this way of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance by tithes being eſtabliſht by the Laws of the Land, people are bound in conſcience to obey the Law (except they can ſhew that it interfears with the Law of God) in paying of them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Ye muſt be ſubject not only for wrath, but for conſcience ſake.</hi> And therefore a perſon may as well pick the money out of a Miniſters pocket, as defraud him of any due; the latter being as much to be abſtained from as the former; becauſe both are forbidden' by the ſame Law.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Another duty is, <hi>Fervent Prayer for them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fervent Prayer.</note> 1 Theſ. 5.25. <hi>Brethren, pray for us.</hi> So <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18. Thus when <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> went forth to preach, they were <hi>recommended by the Brethren to the grace of God, viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> by prayer, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.40. People ſhould pray, that God would qualifie their Miniſters with ſufficient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities for diſcharge of their place. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18, 19. <hi>Col,</hi> 4.3, 4. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.1. that he would <hi>deliver them from wicked and unreaſonable men,</hi> ver. 2. and all other dangers and calamities; and direct them to ſpeak fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the peoples capacities, underſtandings, affections, temptations; and ſuitably and ſeaſonably to all their occaſions.</p>
            <p>And truly, great need have people to pray for their Miniſters;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:116122:23"/>1. Becauſe it is of all callings the moſt difficult: which made the Apoſtle cry out,<note place="margin">Gouge.</note> 
               <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> 2 Cor. 2.16. The Miniſters office is, to quicken ſuch as are dead in ſins; raiſe up and reſtore ſuch as are fallen; comfort the troubled in conſcience; ſtrengthen the weak; encourage the faint-hearted; confound the obſtinate; ſtand againſt all adverſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; with many other the like; all which are very difficult things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe faithfull Miniſters are more oppoſed by Satan, and his inſtruments than any other ſort of men whatſoever.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.1</note> When <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſtood before the Angell of the Lord to receive his Commiſſion, <hi>Satan</hi> ſtood at his right hand to reſiſt him. As ſoone as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was pubickely ſet apart to performe his Miniſteriall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Satan</hi> ſet upon him in the wilderneſſe <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. <hi>begin.</hi> And ever after, the Scribes, Phariſees, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sadduces, and other limbes of the Divell perſecuted him from time to time. And in our own times, we ſee the ſtorm of the fury of the Quakers, and other Sectaries, as alſo of profane, looſe and ungodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, falls eſpecially upon the Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe their failing in duty is moſt dangerous; for if they periſh, many periſh with them, they are like the Admirall Ship that caries the lanthorn where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the whole fleet is guided; if that miſcarry all the reſt are at a loſſe. As when <hi>Peter</hi> ſlipt aſide out of the way, many Jewes and <hi>Barnabas</hi> alſo was carried away with them. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.13. O therefore let your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters never be forgotten in your prayers!</p>
            <p>A gratefull memoriall<note place="margin">A gratfull me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall.</note> of them, when dead and gon, or removed to ſome other place. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116122:23"/> 
               <hi>Remember thoſe your Rulers</hi> (ſo it ſhould be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) <hi>who have ſpoken to you the word of God.</hi> Let their <hi>memory be bleſſed,</hi> (as <hi>Solomons</hi> phraiſe is <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.7.) So as to bleſſe and praiſe God for them, and for the benifit you reaped from their labours while you did enjoy them; as alſo, to praiſe them, and ſpeake well of them; as the LXX render that place. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Remember them alſo, ſo as to take all occaſions of manifeſting your reſpects unto them, if they be yet alive, and only removed from you, by deſiring and rejoycing to ſee them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Thus it was with the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Paul.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>When Timothy came from you to us, he brought us glad tidings of your faith and charity, and that you have good remembrance of us al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, deſiring greatly to ſee us.</hi> Or, if they be dead, by ſhewing the kindneſſe of the Lord to their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Such a remembrance of them, as it is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honour that living people can do to their deceaſed, or departed Paſtors, ſo it wilbe an excellent means to keep them free from the infection and ſeduction of falſe teachers; to eſtabliſh them in the truth they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from thoſe Miniſters; and to keep them ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the way of righteouſneſſe, wherein thoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters walked before them.</p>
            <p>Well, you have now heard what duties you owe unto your Miniſters; Now is there any of you that can or dare deny theſe things to be the word of God? If ſo ſtand forth, and ſpeake, that we may know Chriſtians from Heathens. But if you cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg this that I have ſpoken (for the ſubſtance of every duty) to be the expreſſe word and will of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116122:24"/> God, then conſider how you will ever be able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare it another day to God and your own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, if being informed of your duty you do not practiſe it, but remaine diſobedient and rebellious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of God. But I hope better things of you &amp;c. But more particularly.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Be carefull to <hi>render to all</hi> (and therefore to your Miniſters) <hi>their dues;</hi> as you are required to do. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. You uſe to call their tithes their dues, but you have ſeen there are many more dues, belong to Miniſters from their people beſides them; and which you ſhould make as much conſcience of paying, and be every whit as carfull to com out of their debt for, as for them. And therefore, I ſay, be carefull to render, as to <hi>Ceſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Ceſars;</hi> to the Civill Magiſtrate; what belongs to him; ſo to God the things that are Gods; and to his Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors (Eccleſiaſticall Magiſtrats) the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them. I ſhall ſteele and ſtrengthen this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, by backing it onely with this one conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration taken from,</p>
            <p>The Intereſt you have in them, for the benifit and behoofe of your Soules. All that we Miniſters have or are, is yours. <hi>Paul, Apollos, and Cephas are yours.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>We are your ſervants for Jeſus ſake.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. Our<note n="a" place="margin">A Miniſters gifts are the Town-ſtock, given for the good of the ſoules both of rich and poore. <hi>Gurn.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Abilities</hi> are for your Edification. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11, 12. —<hi>he gave ſome Paſtors and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,—for the Edifying the body of Chriſt.</hi> Our <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> alſo is for the ſame end. viz. <hi>for your Edification, not your deſtruction.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8. Whence there ariſes a great and neceſſary dependance of people upon their Miniſters for their Soules good; inſomuch that it's
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116122:24"/> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, in any ordinary way, that ever you ſhould come to Heaven but by there help. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From us you receive the meanes which God hath ordained for the bringing you to Salvation. <hi>To us is committed the word of reconciliation.</hi> Saith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. And we are his Embaſſadours, ſent with Commiſſion and authority about the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt buſineſſe that ever was taken in hand, even the treating and concluding a peace between God and your Soules. To us alſo is committed the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments and we are the <hi>Keepers of Gods Seales,</hi> ſo as that you cannot have them, but from our hands. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Let a man ſo account of us as of the ſtewards of the myſteries of God.</hi> Yea, to us are committed the <hi>Keies of the Kingdom of heaven. Mat.</hi> 16.19. We have that authority from God to aſſure you in his name (according to Scripture-rules) of the pardon of ſuch ſins as trouble your conſciences, as no man in the world hath beſides. Yea,</p>
            <p n="2">2. You do not onely receive the outward meanes of your ſalvation from us, but (which is far more) by us God gives you his Spirit, and ſaving grace alſo, and conveies it into your hearts. <hi>God,</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>hath made us able Miniſters of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not of the letter, but of the Spirit,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. Inſomuch that where there is any truth of grace, ſome Miniſter or other was the Spirituall Father to beget it, or water it in you. For thus much thoſe emphaticall queſtions of the Apoſtle amount unto. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. <hi>This only would I learn of you, Receaved ye the Spirit by the workes of the Law, or by the hearing of faith? and Rom.</hi> 10.14. <hi>How ſhall they beleive in him of whom they have not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116122:25"/> heard? and how ſhall they heare with out a Preacher?</hi> So that you ſee, all we have, or are is yours i. e. for your good; as a candle is made to give light unto others; and nurſes are ſtock't with milke for their nurſlings ſakes: now every one uſes to be carefull of their own;<note place="margin">Sic vos non vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis &amp;c.</note> and make much of that which is their own, and not be wanting in any due concernment thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Take heed of whatſoever is contrary to that duty you owe to your Miniſters: and do not pleaſe your ſelves in the neglect of your duty with ſuch a fooliſh conceit as this, <hi>That we ſpeake only for our own ends,</hi> when we tell you of theſe things. No! when we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with your duty to our ſelves <hi>'tis not</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeakes concerning the contribution ſent unto him by the Church of <hi>Philippi) becauſe we deſire theſe things</hi> (principally and with reſpect only to our ſelves) <hi>but we deſire fruit that may abound to your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. Phil.</hi> 4.17. And yet if it were ſo? who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes good counſell from a Lawyer, or wholſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections from a Phiſician, out of a conceit that they ſpeake only for their fee; but I ſay that is not the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but for your own ſakes: for (alas!) what is it to us (comparatively and farther than as we ſympathize with you in your weale or woe) if you will not heare, and obey, and be ſaved? Do we deſire any thing but what makes for your owne good, and turns to your own account, and by performance whereof, you will be the greateſt gainers your ſelves? O therefore be not ſo mad and ſpitefull as to prejudice and wrong your own Soules, for, the doing us a little diſpleaſure: As it is in matter of tithes; would not you count that man brutiſhly and ſenſeleſly wilfull and malicious, who
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116122:25"/> ſhould let his ground ly fallow, and thereby looſe his own nine parts, on purpoſe to hinder his Miniſter of his tenth? why, ſo is it in any other duty: by the neglect thereof, you prejudice your ſelves nine parts at leaſt to our tenth i. e. You do infinitely more wrong your ſelves thereby than you do us. But I ſhall ſpeake a little more particulary concerning each of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned duties. 1. Deſpiſe not their Calling 2 Be not diſaffected to their Perſons. 3. Neglect not their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions. 4. Diſobey not their Commands. 5. Be not unſubmiſſive to their Cenſurs. 6. Fret not at their Reproof. 7. Slight not their Example. 8. Wrong them not in their good names. 9. Grudge not their maintenance. 10. Ceaſe not to Pray for them. Laſtly Forget them not.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Take heed of ſlighting,</hi> and lightly eſteeming, much more of vilifying and contemning <hi>your Miniſters;</hi> count them not indifferencies, conveniencies, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities which may very well be ſpared: much leſſe do not groane under them as your burdens, and epidemicall grievances, whoſe roome you had rather have than their company: eſteeme them not the ſcum and refuſe of the world, the filth and offſcourng of all things; nor like <hi>Jereboams</hi> Prieſts, the meaneſt of the people, ſo as to<note n="a" place="margin">Precedency any mans ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Miniſters: eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mammoniſt' every yonger Brother, every <hi>upſtart of</hi> the <hi>firſt head</hi> muſt have the place of us. To the gay cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every one ſaith, <hi>ſit here in the beſt roome:</hi> but unto us, <hi>ſtand thou there or ſit here under my foot-ſtoole. Thus Children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves proudly againſt the ancient and the baſe againſt the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble.</hi> Eſa 3.4. <hi>Downs</hi> Treat. An Amulet. p. 16.</note> poſt-poſe them to every <hi>Thing</hi> that lookes like a Gentleman or hath got but a few fine clothes. O Sirs! would you dare to carry your ſelves ſo towards Chriſt if he were perſonally here on earth? why, 'tis all one in effect, if you will believe his own word. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16. <hi>He that deſpiſeth you deſpiſeth me.</hi> The dirt that is caſt in the Miniſters face, beſmears, and beſpatters Chriſt. And they that ſlight his Miniſters would ſerve him ſo too: they that miſuſed the <hi>Servants</hi> dealt no better with the <hi>Son, Mat.</hi> 21.35, 39. compared. And cerain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch a ſin as this ſhall not go unpuniſhed: Princes and States have alwayes been very tender of their Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116122:26"/> deeply reſenting, and ſeverely puniſhing (to their power) any affront put upon them. Thus did <hi>David.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.6. <hi>and</hi> 12.31. And the <hi>Romans</hi> extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht <hi>Corinth</hi> for violating their Embaſſadors, though the violation were ſo ſmall, that <hi>Florus</hi> could not tell whether it were <hi>Voce,</hi> or <hi>manu.</hi> Do you think then that Chriſt will take it well at your hands, and put up pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently thoſe wrongs and affronts you put upon his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors?<note place="margin">Pſ. 105.15, 1.</note> No; he that <hi>reproved Kings for their ſakes,</hi> will not take it at your hands, nor let you ſcape ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free. You may ſee what to expect, (and learn wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom too from thence, if you are not hardned to your ſin) by what God hath threatned againſt, and inflicted upon others for this ſin. <hi>Chriſt</hi> tells the Jewes, the <hi>vineyard ſhould be let out to other husbandmen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 21.41.</note> and the <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> (i. e. the means of grace whereby they ſhould be brought to happineſſe) <hi>taken from them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 43.</note> 
               <hi>and beſtow'd upon others (ſc.</hi> the Gentiles) for their <hi>miſuſing his meſſengers</hi> and ſervants.<note place="margin">v. 35.</note> There is a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in the next Chapter but one, he threatens them with <hi>temporall</hi> judgments, <hi>viz,</hi> the deſolation of the Temple, and, as an attendant thereon, the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction of their Ceremoniall Worſhip for the ſame ſin. <hi>c.</hi> 23.37, 38. Which did ſhortly after come to paſſe. And ſo, long before that, their <hi>Babyloniſh Captivity</hi> is charged upon the ſcore of this ſin, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16, 17. <hi>They mocked the meſſengers of God, and deſpiſed his words, and miſuſed his prophets, untill the wrath of the Lord roſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his people, till there was no remedy, therefore he brought upon them the King of the Chaldees</hi> &amp;c And if God hath puniſht this ſin ſo ſeverely in this world, O what ſeverity then may they expect from Chriſt in the day of retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the greateſt part of whoſe religion is to heape indignities and diſgraces upon his Miniſters and Meſſengers!<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and to belch out blaſphemies (for that is the term <hi>Paul</hi> uſes concerning diſgracefull
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116122:26"/> ſpeeches of them) againſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Take heed of entertaining any malice,</hi> or hatred, yea of giving way to the leaſt grudge, illwill, animoſity, or diſaffection to them. It's a ſigne of a wretched miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant, ſuch an one as <hi>Ahab,</hi> who ſold himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe, to hate a Meſſenger of God.<note place="margin">1 Kin. 22.8.</note> O therefore do not requite all their love and kindneſſe and paines to your precious ſoules ſo ill! Yet (Alas!) this is the temper of the ingratefull world: of whome the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>Chriſt</hi> may complaine, as <hi>David</hi> of ſome in his time, <hi>They compaſſed me about with words of hatred, and fought againſt me without a cauſe, for my love they are my adverſaries, — and have rewarded me evill for good, and hatred for my love. Pſal.</hi> 109.3, 4, 5. They are the Miniſters of all others, who are made the cheife butt, againſt which many perſons do ſhoot all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venomed arrowes of their rage and malice: and no ſort of men, I dare ſay, are more odious to a number of looſe, untractable perſons, ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> than they: who are many of them, ſo deſperatly bent and furiouſly driven on with a rage reaching up to heaven, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then their bloud, (if they could tell how to come at it (and utter extirpation, would quench their thirſt, and ſatisfy their revengefull hearts, (as it was with <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias</hi> concerning <hi>John the Baptiſt:</hi>) But, as we ſay, <hi>Curſt cowes have ſhort hornes,</hi> ſo ſome that have ſpoken big ſwelling words of vanity againſt Miniſters and Miniſtry, breathing out threatings, and deſigning their utter ruine and deſtruction, have, been not only defeated, and diſappointed in their intended miſcheif, but the <hi>wheel is brought upon them ſelves,</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.26.) whereby they are bruiſed, and cruſht and threſht; and ſo their <hi>faces are filled with ſhame,</hi> as 'tis ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.16. So that we have ſeen of late daies the propheticall imprecation of <hi>Moſes</hi> upon the enemies of <hi>Levi,</hi> notably verified, <hi>Smite through the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116122:27"/> loines of them that riſe up againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not againe, Deut.</hi> 33.11.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Take heed of non-attendance upon them for inſtruction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> neglect not ſeeking unto them <hi>Privatly</hi> for ſatisfaction and reſolution, a very common and continuall fault, the duty being ſildome or never practiſed in many places: ſo that whereas the doores of Lawyers and Phy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitians are thronged many times with attendants, poore Miniſters may ſit longe enough before any one will come to the mon ſuch an errand: though the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer be coſtly, and this they may have upon free-coſte, only for asking<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but however</p>
            <p>Neglect not frequenting the <hi>publicke Aſſemblys,</hi> for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction there. <hi>Forſake not the Aſsembling of your ſelves together, as the manner of ſome</hi> (a great many now a daies,) <hi>is: Heb.</hi> 10.25. 'Tis a ſign of ſome ſad diſtemper hanging upon the ſoule, when perſons either have no ſtomack at all to their ſpirituall food, or prefer unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory ſtuffe, yea infectious traſh, before wholſome proviſion. Therefore let neither profaneſſe, flothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor preſumption, detaine you from Church. Nay ramble not from your own Paſtor if he be in any meaſure able and faithfull. A rolling ſtone gathers no moſſe, and rambling Chriſtians cannot grow much either in grace or knowledge. And therefore let not a gadding humor drive you from your own Church. And when you are there;</p>
            <p>Be not drowſy, ſleepy, careleſſe, heedleſſe, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hearers: let not your heads be like leaking veſſells, letting that go out at one eare, which you take in at the other: when you bring your bodies in to the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, leave not your ſoules behind you. But <hi>be ſwift to heare Jam.</hi> 1.19. Heare as for your lives, when you are hearing the word of life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Take heed of contemning their Authority, and diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their commands and directions:</hi> Heareby a light miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirſion
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116122:27"/> may grow up into a grand tranſgreſſon; an inconſiderable anomy an diniquity, may ſwell into an hainous and heavy enormity. For, as <hi>obedience is better then ſacrifice, and to hearken then the fat of rams;</hi> ſo <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion is as the ſin of witchcraft, and ſtubborneſſe is as iniquity, and idolatry.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22.23. Thinke not your ſelves wiſer than your teachers, ſo as proudly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict and oppoſe them. A ſin not of the leaſt mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude: for it is ſet as a brand of infamy upon thoſe that were guilty of it; and as an inſtance of a notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſin. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Thy people are as they that ſtrive with the Preiſt.</hi> And therefore threatned to be puniſht pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.12. <hi>The man that will do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuously and will not hearken to the Prieſt (that ſtandeth to Miniſter there before the Lord thy God:) or unto the judge, even that man ſhall dy, and thou ſhalt put away the evill from Iſaerl.</hi> And actually cenſured by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14. <hi>If any man obey not our word by this Epiſtle, note that man, and have no company with him, that he may be aſhamed.</hi> And truly, methinkes, theſe words of Chrſts <hi>(Mat.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall bind on earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven)</hi> ſhould be as ſo many thunderclaps to ſtrike terror into the conſciences of all ſtuborn and rebellious perſons, who diſobey and neglect to heare their Miniſters, and thereby incur Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſaſticall cenſures, that they are not only condemned and cenſured by them, but by God likewiſe: and beleive it, ſirs, its no playing and dallying with ſuch edg-tooles. O therefore take heed leaſt you find cauſe one day to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile your folly heerin, when 'tis too late; and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of your ſelves as he in <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.13. <hi>How have I hated inſtruction,</hi> — and <hi>have not obeyed the voice of my teachers, nor inclined mine eare to them that inſtructed me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Take heed of impatience under their cenſures,</hi> or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing thoughts of them, as if they were but <hi>bruta fulmina,</hi> blunt weapons, like cannons charged with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116122:28"/> only, which make a great noiſe, but do no executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or like a bee that hath loſt his ſting, which though it may humme, yet it cannot hurt. True; they wound not the body, nor prejudice the eſtate (directly and immediately,) yet are never the leſſe terrible for that, for (like lightning that melts the Sword, and meddles not with the Scabbard,) they ſeize upon the ſoule, and puniſh perſons in a ſpirituall way: they turn them out of dooers, as I may ſo ſay, (as maſters do unruly ſervants,) by baniſhing them from communion with the Church, they make them to faſt (as Parents do unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward children many times,) by depriving them of the bread of life in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper. Whereby ſuch perſons are in the ſtate of Publicans and heathens. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. Yea like dogs and ſwine. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6. Which ſurely is no contemptible matter. Yea by theſe cenſures they are bound over to the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of God, with ſuch ſtrong cords, which ('tis true, they may unty by Repentance, but) they ſhall never be able to breake and diſintangle themſelves from, by all their impenitence, and contempt, or any ſuch like courſes.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">Is he that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth thee, thy ſuperior? Thine anger is undutifull. Is he thy friend? It is ungratefull, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rein.</note>6. <hi>Take heed of being angry with them for their Reproofes.</hi> Wee Miniſters are too apt of our ſelves to be mealie-mouth'd many times, and let you alone in your ſins for feare of your diſpleaſure. A pettiſh patient maketh the Chirurgeon ſearch the wound leſſe than is neceſſary to a through cure. Now, do not you help forward this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor in us, and make us deale more unfaithfully with your ſoules than otherwiſe we ſhould do. Had you not better heare the worſt of it now, while there may be remedy, than feele the miſery of it hereafter when 'tis too late to helpe it? And yet how few conſider this? Seldome ſhall one meet with a profeſſor that can take a cloſe reproofe patiently: much leſſe then is it to be found in others, moſt perſons count their Miniſters their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116122:28"/> greateſt enemy, that deale moſt freely, plainly,<note place="margin">Reprooſes are good phyſick, but they have an unpleaſing farewell: 'tis hard for men not to vomit them up againe in the face of him that gives them. <hi>Gurn.</hi>
               </note> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and impartially with them. We cannot ſpeake to them ſo tenderly, but they are ready to thinke, it is to diſgrace them, or out of ill will to them, or that we make more ado than needs, or make them worſe than they are, and are ready to ſay, Looke to your ſelfe, you ſhall not anſwer for me. Yea they would, if they could, ſtop his mouth from preaching, who would ſtop there courſe in ſinning, as <hi>Amaziah</hi> did the prophets, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.16. Ay but one day, ſooner or later, you will ſee your own folly herein, and befoole your ſelves, as he did, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.12. Saying, <hi>How have I hated inſtruction and my heart deſpiſed reproofe?</hi> And therefore give not way to this humor in your ſelves, but rather be angry with thy ſelfe for thy ſin, and thou wilt love him that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to free thee from it. Count it thy diſeaſe, thy burden, thine <hi>Enemy,</hi> and thou wilt be thankfull to him that diſcovers this <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> and adminiſters phyſick for thy cure; that lends thee his hand to throw off this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; that forewarnes thee of this <hi>Enemy,</hi> and helps thee to fight againſt it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Beware of diſregarding their example as not worthy your obſervation, or Imitation.</hi> For though, 'tis true, in matters of <hi>Doctrine</hi> they are not infallible, nor in matters of <hi>Practiſe</hi> impeccable and unblameable, yet as they know their duty and the way they ſhould walke in, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than others, (ordinarily,) ſo likewiſe they do many times, (and I ſuppoſe, uſually,) obtaine more grace of God than others to be faithfull in their ſtations, and to be more brightly burning and ſhining lights than others: it being but agreeable to Gods ordinary method of providence, to qualify perſons for thoſe places he calls them to; ſo that they being ſet in<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 5.15.</note> an eminent, obſervable place, are inabled accordingly, through grace, to be of exemplary lives. This exemplarineſſe then being beſtowed upon them, partly for the imitation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116122:29"/> ſhould not lightly be accounted of, as not worth the taking notice of. People ſhould not hide their eyes from beholding the<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>light</hi> of their Miniſters <hi>good workes,</hi> much leſſe looke upon it through falſe glaſſes, but ſo to ſee and obſerve it, as to glorify God, by an imitation thereof.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Beware of wronging and wounding them in their good names, either</hi> by <hi>raiſing,</hi> or <hi>receiving</hi> any ill report of them: a very frequent and common practiſe with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. As it was formerly, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.30. <hi>Son of man, the children of thy people are ſtill talking againſt thee by the walls, and in the doors of their houſes,</hi> ſo it is ſtill. How of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten are the good names of Miniſters thruſt thorough with the ſharp ſwords of backbiting tongues? 'tis the common trade that many drive, to caſt dirt upon them, wherever they come, but eſpecially if they chance to ſpy any naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or humane infirmity in ſuch an one, then they have ſome ſcratch for their itch; preſently all the town and country ſhall ring of it; inſtead of covering it with the garment of charity, they (like curſed <hi>Cham</hi>) proclaim, and divulge it all abroad to his diſgrace. Yea, <hi>aut invenient aut facient;</hi> rather then faile, they will invent ſome lye or other to <hi>blaſpheame</hi> them, and beſpatter their good name with all. A fearefull ſin, which you ſhould be very fraid of. For ſaith God, <hi>Wherefore were ye not afraid to ſpeake againſt my ſervant Moſes? Num.</hi> 12.8. q. d. What! to ſpeake againſt my ſervant! againſt Moſes! to diſgrace any one whom I put ſpeciall markes of honour upon! I wonder you would offer it. Nay, 'tis a ſin of ſuch an ugly aſpect, that I wonder you durſt be ſo foole-hardy as to venture upon it; that you were not afraid of it. And therefore take heed of being either the <hi>Parent,</hi> or <hi>Nurſe</hi> of ſuch a baſtard, yea diveliſh practiſe, as this; but remember, you muſt be reſponſible both for your <hi>Eares</hi> and <hi>Tongues</hi> in this caſe.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Grudge not their maintenance.</hi> Beware either of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining</hi> the whole, or <hi>defrauding</hi> them of any part of that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:116122:29"/> which is their due either by the Lawes of God or man.<note place="margin">It was once ſaid, <hi>What ſhall we give the man of God?</hi> 1 Sam. 9.7. but now eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſaith, <hi>Come let us take the houſes of God in poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> Pſal. 83.12. When <hi>Moſes</hi> built the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berncle, he was ſain to ſtay the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, they were ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>Exod.</hi> 36.5, 6. but now would God we could ſtay their hands from robbing the Tabernacle. <hi>Down.</hi>
               </note> This is plainly neither better nor worſe, than a rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of God and ſo you will find it one day. A point, that, if I miſtake not, much concernes both <hi>Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators,</hi> and <hi>Compounders. Impropriators;</hi> who, if their be any ſuch ſin as Sacriledge (which I know no reaſon to deny) are highly guilty of it. For if either on the one hand the Law of god concerning tithes as to the ſubſtance of it, be ſtill in force, ſo that ſuch a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be due to the Miniſters of the Goſpell as was to the Preiſts and Levites under the Law, then Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators have no right to them; or if on the other hand, that Law be not in force now, yet this is clear, that the perſons who firſt aſſigned ſuch portions out of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, did intentionally dedicate them unto God, and ſet them apart for the maintenance of his worſhip and ſervice (however ſometimes their might be ſome error in the manner) and ſo they became hallowed things and ſuch as did belong to God, and conſequently not aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble afterwards by any man, or company of men what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, it being both againſt the doners will, which none ought to <hi>diſanull.</hi> (Gal. 3.15.) And the nature of hallowed things, which ought not to be put to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe. Whence we read that the cenſers uſed by <hi>Corah</hi> and his complices, though it was ſtrange fire that was offered in them, yet becauſe they were <hi>offered before the Lord,</hi> therefore they were hallowed and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be turned <hi>into broad plates for the Altar,</hi> that ſo they might not be put to any common uſe againe. <hi>Num.</hi> 16.37.38. Beſides, being hallowed things, they belong pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily unto God <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.30. Now he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Miniſters to be his receivers. <hi>Num.</hi> 18 8.9. <hi>The Lord ſpake unto Aaron, behold I have alſo giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n thee the charge of my heave-offerings of all the hallowed things of all the children of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 27 30.</note> 
               <hi>unto thee have I given them
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116122:30"/> by reaſon of the annointing, and to thy ſons by an ordinance for ever,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that what is due to God is to be paid to them. <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.8. —<hi>Let the treſpaſs be recompenſed unto the Lord, even to the Prieſt,</hi> q. d. the Prieſts (then, and ſo Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters now) are the Lords Receivers; ſo that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Lord muſt be paid to them; and what is paid to them, it is all one as if it were paid into Gods own hands; for he allows it upon account, and gives an acquittance and diſcharge for it, as if received by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And therefore except theſe perſons can ſhow a Commiſſion from God for their receiving of them, ſuch as he hath given to his Miniſters, I wou d fain know how they will be ever able to anſwer it to God, and acquit themſelves of the guilt of ſacriledge. I might adde that theſe revenues being deſigned for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Gods ſervice, as I ſaid, <hi>i. e.</hi> of thoſe, whoſe buſineſs and particular calling it is to be employed about Gods worſhip, and ſervice, how can they have <hi>any right to eat of the Altar, who ſerve not at the Altar?</hi> How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and unjuſt a thing is it, that they that are not ſo much as in a capacity of doing the work, ſhould have (in a manner) all the wages? Miniſters plow and ſow (as I may ſo ſay) and Impropriators reap the crop and benefit. Miniſters <hi>plant the vineyard,</hi> and Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priators <hi>eat the fruit thereof.</hi> Miniſters <hi>feed the flock,</hi> and Impropriators <hi>eat the milke,</hi> and take the fleece <hi>of the flocke.</hi> This is not ſo ſtrange a thing, in many places in <hi>England</hi> (how abſurd and ſinfull ſoever it be) as the Apoſtle makes it, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.</p>
            <p>And then for <hi>Compounders,</hi> who <hi>take</hi> (I will not ſay, ſteal) <hi>a Gooſe and ſtick down a feather only,</hi> (as we uſe to ſay) that have large eſtates and proportions, and yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low but ſome petty inconſiderable <hi>Compoſition</hi> in lieu of all, perhaps not a tithe of their tithe, let them ſeriouſly conſider, whether Preſcription and Cuſtome will be a ſufficient Plea at Gods Tribunall. If a tenth be ſtill due
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:116122:30"/> by Gods Law, (as I think the learnedeſt of them cannot diſprove) then I am ſure that the Law of man will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver excuſe them, that limits it to a twentieth, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it may be ſcarce a fourtieth part. For though the Law of the Land may augment and enlarge, yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it cannot contract and abridge, what the Law of God gives and allowes. An inferiour power cannot take away any thing that a ſuperiour gives, though it may give more. True,<note place="margin">Lev. 27.</note> in ſome caſes we read of an exchange allowable; that the hallowed thing might be turned into money, but then an indifferent price was to be ſet upon it by the Prieſt, and he was not bound to change a Noble for nine pence. I have ſpoken the more concerning theſe things, becauſe perſons ſwallow them ſo eaſily without chewing, and conſidering, that <hi>though they be ſweet in the mouth, they will be bitter in the belly, and in the end.</hi> And therefore beware of <hi>devouring holy things</hi> in any way whatſoever, but ſee that you keep a good conſcience in theſe things, wherein ſo many do offend, that you may be able to purge your ſelves, and make that proteſtation which the <hi>Jewes</hi> were commanded to do, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.12, 13, 14. <hi>When thou haſt made an end of tithing all the tithes of thine increaſe—then thou ſhalt ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord thy God, I have brought away the hallowed things out of mine houſe, —according to all thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which thou haſt commanded me: I have not tranſgreſſed thy Commandements, neither have I forgotten them: I have not eat thereof in my mourning,</hi> i. e. (as ſome expound it) What want ſoever I have been in, yet durſt I never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve my neceſſity by robbing God of his part, by appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priating to my ſelf, or imploying to my own private uſe any thing that did belong to him.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Ceaſe not to pray for them</hi> He is counted uncivill, that, if he doth but paſs by one at plow, or meet a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller on the road, will not bid him <hi>God speed:</hi> and ſurely he is both unchriſtian and undutifull, that will
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:116122:31"/> not pray for the continuance and increaſe of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters gifts and graces, and for a bleſſing upon his labours. Yet many pray rather for a quiet and peaceable man, as they call him, who will be content with any thing they give him; not inquiſitive into their converſations; not buſie in prying into their faults, but rather winking at them; ſuffering them to walk in their ſinfull wayes, and take no notice of it. O this is the man for their turn! Such a one they pray heartily their Miniſter may be; but for his ability and fidelity in the diſcharge of his place, and other things of the like nature, they never ſo much as wiſh for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forget not your Miniſters,</hi> and their <hi>labour of love</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you for your ſouls good. Let them not have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſay of you, according to the old Proverb, <hi>Out of ſight, out of mind:</hi> hereby you will diſcover both your ingratitude and folly. It's taxed as a foul blemiſh upon that City which was <hi>delivered by the wiſdome of a poor wiſe man, that no man remembred the ſame poor man,</hi> Eccl. 9.15. And it was the deſtruction of <hi>Joaſh,</hi> that <hi>he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred not the kindneſs which</hi> Jehoiada <hi>had done to him,</hi> 2 Chron. 24.22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O therefore let it never be ſaid, that you have ſo ſoon forgotten all thoſe wholſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions they gave you, and thoſe other kindneſſes they ſhewed to your ſouls, ſo that you ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a <hi>gratefull memoriall</hi> of them ſo long as you live.</p>
            <p>Take heed of making default in any of theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; and think not that an inconſiderable under-rate Compoſition will ſerve for theſe dues: for aſſure your ſelves, that if either you detain or defraud your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of them, God will fine you in treble dammages at leaſt. And therefore be carefull in paying all theſe debts and duties you owe to them, that thereby you may make it appear, that you <hi>Know them</hi> (and your duty to them) <hi>which labour among you, and are over you, and admoniſh you.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
